<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On the coming of Christ</title>
            <author>W. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T67A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95625)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2373:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>On the coming of Christ</title>
                  <author>W. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>iii, [1], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>DFo copy, reel 2373, missing title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Messiahship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXIV, 3 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:153637:1"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:153637:1"/>
            <head>THE <hi>AUTHOR</hi>'s PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the <hi>READER,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>READER, if thou begin to read; read through and paſs no Cenſure on any Thing, 'till thou haſt read every Thing. 'Tis not Wiſdom to judge of a Matter, before we hear it; and if it be not Wiſdom, 'tis Shame and Folly, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. It may be thou wilt ſay as thoſe did, Acts 17, <hi>What will this Babbler ſay? Thou bringeſt ſtrange Things to our Ears;</hi> to tell us of <hi>Chriſt's Coming before the general Judgement;</hi> and of <hi>a firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection before all be raiſed;</hi> and of <hi>Saints reigning a Thouſand Years upon Earth;</hi> and of <hi>a new Heaven and a new Earth,</hi> and of <hi>the burning of the Old;</hi> and of a great many other new Things which we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of before; we would fain know what they mean. I truſt it will appear they are <hi>not new, but old;</hi> they may be <hi>new</hi> to <hi>ſome</hi> Men, but I cannot ſay 'tis their Honour; and though theſe Things be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as Truths with <hi>ſome</hi> Men <hi>now;</hi> yet <hi>not with all;</hi> 'tis more than poſſible they will appear to be ſo when I ſhall be here no more. But 'tis <hi>not a new</hi> Thing <hi>to mock at the Reſurrection</hi> of the Dead, as they did, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.32; nor <hi>to ſcoff at the Coming of Chriſt,</hi> as thoſe 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, 4. But, <hi>Be not Mockers, leſt your Bands be made ſtrong.</hi> Why ſhould it be tho't incredible that God will raiſe <hi>ſome</hi> from the dead <hi>before others,</hi> or that Chriſt will come <hi>before ſome Men</hi> look for him? <hi>The Reſurrection
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:153637:2"/>of Chriſt</hi> ſeemed to the <hi>Apoſtles themſelves</hi> but <hi>as idle Tales,</hi> when they firſt heard of it; <hi>Luke</hi> 24.11. And though Chriſt himſelf had hold them of it before,—<hi>ver.</hi> 7. All Things will ſeem <hi>new,</hi> to ſuch as never ſaw or heard of them before: And there will be a Time when all Things ſhall be made <hi>new, Rev.</hi> 21.5. And there is a Treaſury which ſome Men have, in which are Things <hi>new</hi> as well as <hi>old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it may poſſibly be, that ſome are of a quite contrary Mind; and will ſay that here is nothing new, but what hath been ſaid over and over by others, and that long ago. But what hath been ſaid by others every one doth not know; and it may be, here may be ſome Things ſaid which have not been ſaid by others that I know of. But let it be granted that others have written of theſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And if ſo, methinks it ſhould gain the more Reputation, and be the better credited in the World by them that are wiſe.</p>
            <p>Yea, but <hi>ſome</hi> of thoſe who held theſe Opinions have been foully <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in ſome other Things,</hi> and therefore little Heed is to be given to them. 'Tis poſſible it may be ſo: <hi>(humanum eſt errare)</hi> who durſt to eaſt the firſt Stone at them? Neither are ſome Failings in Men, Rules to judge of Truth and Error: <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi> was the good old Way: Detraction from ſome Men will add nothing to the Detractors.</p>
            <p>Some others refuſe to ſtudy Propheſy, as being <hi>too high</hi> and <hi>too hard</hi> for them to underſtand; and many that have expounded Propheſy have been miſtaken: There is a Lion in the Sluggard's Way. 'Tis true, there are <hi>ſome Things</hi> in the <hi>Prophets</hi> hard to be underſtood; and ſo there are in <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> tells us; and yet being given by inſpiration, are profitable. And as to PROPHESY, <hi>We ſhould do well to give Heed to it, as to a Light ſhining in a dark Place,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19. And they are pronounced <hi>bleſſed</hi> that <hi>read and hear Propheſy,</hi> Rev. 1.3. Theſe will loſe the <hi>Marrow,</hi> rather than take Pains to break the <hi>Bones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know 'tis beyond what any Man is able clearly to determine all Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Thing relating to what is here written, and to anſwer all Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning the ſame; yet <hi>by runing to and fro, Knowledge ſhall be increaſed,</hi> Dan. 12.4. And what if I (a poor lame Man) run alſo? But <hi>the Wiſe ſhall underſtand,</hi> ver. 10.</p>
            <p>Yea, but <hi>other Matters</hi> and Things <hi>are of higher Concernment</hi> than theſe. To ſuch I ſay, tho' ſome Things may be of higher Concernment than others; yet no Part of Truth but is of Concernment: And he reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects not any Part of Truth as he ought, that hath not reſpect to every Part of it: And he that thinks the ſubject Matters of this Diſcourſe are of little Concernment, will be found to be miſtaken.</p>
            <p>'Tis more than poſſible, that his Script may fall into the Handds of ſome that are eminent in their own Underſtandings, and are very ſenſible of their own Sufficiency and Abilities in theſe Matters; who have read
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:153637:2"/>theſe and thoſe learned Men, that are of other Opinions; call this and that Man Maſter; (a Vanity reproved by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13; yea by Chriſt himſelf) and ſo conceive they are able <hi>(ex tempore)</hi> to give a full and clear anſwer to all theſe Things, and are reſolved to enquire no further, nor to ſearch the Scriptures whether it be ſo or no. There is more Hope of ſome others than of theſe. Let ſuch know what the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> quoted in Favour of what is here written, are <hi>infallible,</hi> and cannot err: A <hi>Catalogue</hi> of whom are to be ſeen at the End of this Manuſcript.</p>
            <p>But ſome others will ſay that this is an immethodical Thing, and done by an inconſiderable Perſon. I readily comply with thoſe that ſo think, and that it may want that which is called Method; if any do not like it, I cannot help it: I had no Scheme of Things in my Head, when I firſt began: You have it as I had it. Beſides, I do not pretend any Thing to human Learning, being much a Stranger to it: What Time I have ſpent about theſe Things, have been ſhort <hi>Interims</hi> pincht out of my other Occaſions: And if may be, if it were to be done again, it might be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>I might mention ſome others, not a few, who are of <hi>Gallio</hi>'s Mind, that <hi>care for none of theſe Things,</hi> having other Things to care for, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them as cunningly deviſed Fables. I have nothing to ſay to ſuch careleſs ones, but this; that Chriſt will care as little for them another Day.</p>
            <p>It may be I have ſaid too much already to the Reader, and more than a wiſe Man would have ſaid; and more than I ſhould have ſaid, had not there been ſome Neceſſity of it. But I have done, when I have told you that I am a very old Man, and very near another World; having lived far beyond the ſtated Age of Man, and do not know whether I ſhall be able to ſpeak when I come to die; and therefore ſhall leave this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me, which will ſpeak when I ſhall ſpeak here no more; penned partly for my own Satisfaction, and partly with Reſpect to ſome of mine, whoſe Salvation I am caring for, and am willing they ſhould be acquainted with ſuch Truths as theſe are. 'Tis poſſible, and more than poſſible, that I may be miſtaken in ſome Things here written; my Way being little (if not too little) trodden by others. But if ſo, being made ſenſible of it, I ſhall not be backward to acknowledge my Failings. But 'tis no good Logick, nor will it be a convincing Argument to me, to ſay, that what is here written is not ſo. If ſuch an Anſwer would ſuffice, and Diſputes would ſoon be ended; and it might poſſible ſatisfy all but ſuch as have their Eyes in their Heads. And if theſe be not Truths which are here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, or propoſed to Conſideration; thoſe that are of another Opinion, may do well to let us underſtand our Miſtakes, and declare their own Sentiments herein.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153637:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153637:3"/>
            <head>Of the Coming of CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATT. XXIV. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Tell us, when ſhall theſe Things be? And what ſhall be the Sign of thy Coming, and of the End of the World?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Words contain <hi>three Queſtions</hi> propoſed by the Diſciples to Chriſt for Reſolution; (1) <hi>when ſhall theſe Things be?</hi> which Words refer to the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>City:</hi> (2) <hi>What ſhall be the Signs of thy Coming?</hi> This Queſtion ſeems to be grounded upon the <hi>laſt Verſe</hi> of the <hi>former Chapter; ye ſhall not ſee me henceforth, till</hi> &amp;c. implying a Time wherein the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould ſee Chriſt again viſibly; when they ſhould ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is be that comes in the Name of the Lord.</hi> The (3) Queſtion was about <hi>the End of the World, when that ſhould be?</hi> and <hi>what Signs would precede?</hi> That the World ſhould have an End, Chriſt had told them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.40. Now that <hi>theſe are three diſtinct Queſtions,</hi> is evident by <hi>three diſtinct Anſwers</hi> which Chriſt makes to the Diſciples. His <hi>firſt Anſwer,</hi> concerning the Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Temple, begins with a Caution, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Take Heed that no Man deceive you;</hi> and afterwards deſcribes the Miſery of that Nation in many Particulars, as Signs and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153637:4"/>Forerunners of their Ruin, unto ver. 23. See <hi>Luke</hi> 21.20. But this being paſt, no Notice ſhall be taken of it here. The <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>ſecond Queſtion</hi> begins at the 23 ver. of <hi>this Chap.</hi> and continues to the 31 ver. of the 25 <hi>Chap.</hi> and from thence to the End, we have a Deſcription of the general Judgment, and of the End of the World: But <hi>no Signs</hi> preceding either there, or any where elſe in Scripture, that this Writer knows.</p>
            <p>The <hi>main Thing intended in this Script,</hi> is <hi>modeſtly to enquire (not poſitively to conclude any Thing</hi>) concerning a right Underſtanding of the <hi>ſecond Queſtion,</hi> and the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> of Chriſt thereunto, viz. <hi>What Kind of Coming of Chriſt is here to be underſtood?</hi> And here we muſt know, that there are <hi>more</hi> Comings of Chriſt than <hi>two.</hi> There is a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Coming in the Miniſtry. Chriſt came and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Miniſtry of <hi>Noab,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3; and by the Miniſtry of <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 2.17. There is alſo a <hi>providential</hi> Coming of Chriſt in ſtupendous Providences: and it may be of this Coming <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.8; <hi>the Coming of the Lord draws nigh.</hi> Neither of theſe ſeems to be meant here; nor will the Signs laid down of the Coming of Chriſt agree to either of them. For firſt, it cannot be meant of his Coming in the Goſpel <hi>ſpiritually:</hi> for ſo he hath been always Coming, and will be to the End of the World; and <hi>no Signs</hi> can be given of this Coming. The like may be ſaid concerning his Coming in <hi>extraordinary Providences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Comings of Chriſt might be mentioned; but this Coming of Chriſt ſeems to be a <hi>perſonal</hi> Coming: and therefore tis ſaid, <hi>they ſhall ſee the Son of Man Coming,</hi> viz. <hi>perſonally.</hi> Chriſt is ſeldom, if ever, ſtiled <hi>the Son of Man</hi> in any other Coming. Again tis ſaid, <hi>he cometh in the Clouds of Heaven.</hi> Dan. 7.13, <hi>One like the Son of Man, came with the Clouds of Heaven:</hi> Rev. 1.7, <hi>Behold he cometh with Clouds and every Eye ſhall ſee him, and they that have pierced him,</hi> viz. the <hi>Jews, Zech.</hi> 12.10. This Deſcription of Chriſt's Coming in the Clouds of Heaven ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153637:4"/>often mentioned, cannot be underſtood of his Coming <hi>in the Goſpel.</hi> But it may be ſaid, by <hi>Clouds</hi> may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>his Ordinances;</hi> as in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.6. <hi>I will command the Clouds that they rain no more Rain upon it.</hi> To which it is anſwered; 'tis not ſaid there, <hi>the Clouds of Heaven,</hi> as in the fore-mentioned Texts. Secondly, tis anſwered, that <hi>Clouds</hi> are for <hi>Protection</hi> from Danger, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.19; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4.5. for a Defence upon the Glory: and ſo it may be well underſtood here. But, if this ſatisfy not, we muſt know, that <hi>parabolical</hi> Divinity is not argumentative againſt <hi>plain Texts</hi> of Scripture; and we may not forſake the <hi>literal</hi> Interpretation, where tis not contrary to the Analogy of Faith.</p>
            <p>Let us conſider a litter further of ſome of the <hi>Signs</hi> foregoing <hi>this Coming</hi> of Chriſt, and ſee how they will agree with <hi>any other Coming</hi> but a <hi>perſonal</hi> Coming. For the Suddenneſs of it is compared to <hi>Lightening</hi> which is moſt quick, viſible, and alſo terrible, ver. 27. deſcribed alſo by <hi>gathering together of the Eagles, ver.</hi> 28. It cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of he <hi>Roman Eagles,</hi> called <hi>the Abomination of Deſolation:</hi> For that was paſt long ago before the Deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Temple, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. and therefore ſuch an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is foreign from the meaning of that Text. By <hi>Eagles</hi> therefore are to be underſtood <hi>Saints</hi> rather: By the <hi>Carcaſs,</hi> or <hi>Body,</hi> as <hi>Luke</hi> renders it, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>ver.</hi> 24-37. is to be underſtood <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and the Apoſtle 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. ſpeaking of <hi>this Coming of Chriſt,</hi> ſpeaks alſo of <hi>our ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together to him;</hi> foretold by <hi>Jacob</hi> long before his Incarnation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>To him ſhall the gathering of the People be:</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaking of ſuch a fiery tempeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Time as is like to be at this Coming of Chriſt, tells us, that God calls to the Heavens above and to the Earth <hi>to gather together his Saints, Pſal.</hi> 50.3, 4: and in <hi>ver.</hi> 31. of <hi>this Chap.</hi> tis ſaid <hi>he ſhall ſend his Angels with a great' Sound of a Trumpet, to gather together his Elect from one End of Heaven to the other:</hi> which it may be is the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153637:5"/>ſpoken of, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27.12, 13. when the great Trumpet ſhall be blown, and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> which are ready to periſh in the Land of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> ſhall be <hi>gathered one by one, and ſhall worſhip the Lord in the holy Mount of Jeruſalem.</hi> Now, tis probable theſe Gatherings together will be of <hi>all Elect Jews and Gentiles;</hi> done partly by a <hi>Sight</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and partly by the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of Man; of which we may poſſibly ſpeak more fully hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another Sign</hi> of Chriſt's Coming is; <hi>The Sun ſhall be darkned, and the Moon not give her Light, and the Stars fall from Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Let us conſider here, what may be meant by <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> and then ſee how tis a Sign of Chriſt's Coming in the Goſpel. There are <hi>ſome</hi> that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it <hi>literally,</hi> that theſe celeſtial Bodies ſhould be darkened by frequent Eclipſes, and that the Stars ſhould really fall to the Earth. But we know that Eclipſes are ordinary and common Things, and are, and have been in all Ages, and are prodvced by natural Cauſes; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſo underſtood cannot be a <hi>Sign</hi> of Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Goſpel, or any other Way: much leſs by falling of Stars to the Earth, which is a Thing impoſſible; the Diameter of the Earth not being able to contain <hi>one Star.</hi> Beſides, they are by an Ordinance of Heaven ſet to give Light to the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.18: and thoſe Ordinances cannot be changed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.36: therefore ſomething elſe is here meant. Let us ſee what the Scripture ſpeaks to this. Thoſe Words then are <hi>metaphorically</hi> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: For there are <hi>other Suns, Moons</hi> &amp; <hi>Stars,</hi> which we read of in Scripture. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.9, 10. There is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars:</hi> where Superiors both ſupreme and ſubordinate are repreſented under that Notion of <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars.</hi> It may alſo ſignify the <hi>Fall</hi> and Ruin of <hi>States, Monarchs</hi> &amp; <hi>Monarchys.</hi> Hence we read at the Fall of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarchy; of the <hi>darkning of the Sun,</hi> and <hi>the Moon not giving her Light, nor the Stars of Heaven, nor the Conſtellations thereof, Iſai.</hi> 13.10.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153637:5"/>and Chap. 14.12, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid to <hi>fall from Heaven,</hi> and call'd <hi>Lucifer, Son of the Morning.</hi> The Fall of <hi>Idumea</hi> is repreſented to us by the <hi>Hoſt of Heaven being diſſolved,</hi> i. e. Sun Moon and Stars being darkened. Hence we read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6, at the <hi>opening</hi> of the <hi>ſixth Seal,</hi> of <hi>the Sun's becoming black as Sackcloth,</hi> and <hi>the Moon as Blood:</hi> which ſome underſtand of the Fall of the <hi>Roman Pagan Empire:</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.12, at another remarkable Period we read of a <hi>third Part</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened:</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.8, <hi>the fourth Angel poured out a Vial on the Sun,</hi> i.e. the <hi>antichriſtian State,</hi> or <hi>ſome eminent Perſon in it.</hi> We read alſo in <hi>Joel</hi> 3.15, of <hi>the Sun and Moon being darkened, and the Stars withdrawing their Light:</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.31, that <hi>the Sun ſhall be turned into Darkneſs, and the Moon into Blood:</hi> And when will this be? <hi>When he will gather all Nations into the Valley of Jehoſhaphat, and plead with them there,</hi> both Pagan and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Enemies: this ſeems to be their great and laſt Overthrow at <hi>Armageddon;</hi> when <hi>the Kings of the Earth</hi> and of the whole World <hi>ſhall be gathered together to the Battle of that great Day of God Almighty.</hi> Hitherto may be referred that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.6; <hi>when he ſhall judge among the Heathen, and fill the Places with dead Bodies, and ſhall wound the Heads over many Countries.</hi> And it may be tis THEN, <hi>they,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Jews ſhall go forth and look on the Carcaſes of the Men that have tranſgreſſed againſt God,</hi> Iſai. 66.24; for then <hi>by Fire and Sword will the Lord plead with all Fleſh, ver.</hi> 16. A Scheme of this Battle we have in <hi>Ezekiel Chap.</hi> 38 &amp; 39: and Expreſſions of the ſame Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of <hi>pleading againſt them with Sword &amp; Peſtilence and Blood and Fire;</hi> and is all one with that mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, and <hi>Joel</hi> 2. And when this ſhall be, it will be a dark and bloody World indeed; when theſe Suns and Moons are thus darkened and turned into Blood, and ſo many Stars of the firſt Magnitude fall. But when will this be? It will be <hi>in the latter Days,</hi> ver. 11. and <hi>yet long before the laſt Day.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153637:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153637:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153637:7"/>It will be at or about <hi>the Calling of the Jews,</hi> Joel 3.1; and ſpoke of, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37, immediately before this great Deſtruction: then theſe <hi>Suns and Moons will be aſhamed and confounded, when the Lord of Hoſts ſhall reign in Mount Sion and in Jeruſalem, and before his Antients gloriouſly,</hi> Iſai. 24. Thus we ſee what may be meant in this Text by <hi>Sun Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> and what by being <hi>darkened;</hi> by comparing it with other Scriptures. Now let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered how well <hi>this Sign</hi> will agree with the Coming of Chriſt in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The <hi>next Sign</hi> to be taken Notice of as preceding the Coming of Chriſt, is, touching the <hi>Time;</hi> it will be at <hi>ſuch a Time as is unknown to Men or Angels.</hi> Hence he is ſaid to come <hi>as a Thief,</hi> Rev. 16.15; &amp; Chap. 3.3, <hi>Behold I come as a Thief:</hi> And he threatned to <hi>come</hi> to the Church of Sardis <hi>as a Thief, and thou ſhalt not know in what Hour I will come upon thee.</hi> This Coming, will be <hi>ſecretly, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, unexpectedly,</hi> and unavoidably. Furthermore, it will be a <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>general and deep Security;</hi> when <hi>Men ſhall ſay Peace and Safety:</hi> A Time of <hi>Senſuality; as in the Days of</hi> Noah <hi>and</hi> Lott, <hi>Eating and Drinking, Marrying and giving in Marriage:</hi> A <hi>ſleepy World; wiſe Virgins</hi> as well as <hi>fooliſh, ſlumbering and ſleeping,</hi> when Chriſt comes as a Bridegroom; which is <hi>not at the general Judgment;</hi> for the <hi>wiſe</hi> Virgins <hi>will not then be aſleep;</hi> neither will it then be a Time of general Security and Senſuality, as it was in the Days of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lott,</hi> as we ſhall ſhow hereafter: And the Signs of Chriſt's Coming extend to the 30th Ver. of Chap. 25th; <hi>when the Son of Man cometh, ſhall he find Faith on Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let him that Readeth underſtand and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>theſe Signs,</hi> or <hi>any other,</hi> will agree with Chriſt's coming in the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>moſt</hi> Men underſtand this Coming to be <hi>to the laſt Judgment,</hi> and do grant it to be a <hi>perſonal</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; let us now conſider how <hi>all theſe Signs</hi> will agree, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153637:7"/>be Forerunners of Chriſt's coming to the laſt Judgment: And which Coming is ſpoken of <hi>Chap.</hi> 25, from <hi>Ver.</hi> 30th to the <hi>End;</hi> or whether there be <hi>any Signs at all</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Scripture of his <hi>coming</hi> to <hi>the laſt Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here of Neceſſity, ſomething muſt be ſpoken of the THOUSANDS YEARS, and of the State of Things here, during that Time; as alſo of <hi>the firſt Reſurrection,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt in this World,</hi> Rev. 20, and other Things coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Firſt,)</hi> Whether there <hi>be ſuch a Term</hi> of Time or no, as <hi>the Thouſands Years; (Secondly,)</hi> Whether it be <hi>paſt</hi> or <hi>future;</hi> and <hi>(Thirdly,)</hi> The Time <hi>when</hi> it doth <hi>begin,</hi> or <hi>from what Period</hi> it doth commence.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, that there <hi>is ſuch</hi> a Thing or <hi>Term</hi> of Time, is that which hath been aſſerted by Men of Note in all Ages ſince the primative Times; a Catalogue of whom might eaſily be produced if Need were. But this Doctrine of <hi>the Thouſand Years</hi> needs no human Teſtimony: We have a more ſure Word of Propheſy, which we ſhould do well to give Heed unto. In <hi>Rev.</hi> 20, it is expreſs'd no leſs than <hi>five Times over,</hi> a Thouſand Years, and <hi>The Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years,</hi> with an Emphaſis. And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> Chap. 2.3, ſpeaking of <hi>the Day of the Lord, and Perdition of ungodly Men;</hi> tells us, that <hi>one Day with the Lord is a Thouſand Years:</hi> which <hi>ſome</hi> think refers to <hi>this Time:</hi> But whether they do or no, we muſt and ought to believe it: for <hi>this is one of thoſe Sayings that is faithful and true.</hi> Rev. 22. ver. 6; and <hi>if any Man ſhall ſay otherwiſe, and take away from the Words of this Propheſy, God ſhall take away his Part out of the Book of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us enquire what the Scripture ſpeaks to this Point; that there ſhall be a Time in which God will deſtroy the Wicked of the World, and the Enemies of his Church and People; and that there ſhall be a Time of Peace, and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from all perſecuting Power; a Time of great Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153637:8"/>and Happineſs; a Time wherein he will pour out his Spirit in great Abundance from on high, ſuch a Time as was never yet in the World; a Time of refreſhing from the Preſence of the Lord; Times of the Reſtitution of all Things: and <hi>thoſe Times have been ſpoken of by all the holy Prophets ſince the World began.</hi> The Truth is, it is the Time of the Duration of Chriſt's Kingdom in this World; which is to be given to him <hi>after the Deſtruction of the little Horn;</hi> as is clear from <hi>Daniel</hi> 7; and which he is gone to receive for himſelf, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.12.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing ſuch Times and Things have been ſpoken of by <hi>all the holy Prophets,</hi> we will enquire what <hi>every one</hi> of them have ſpoken to theſe Things. We ſhall begin with ISAIAH: <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.2, the Prophet tells of a Time when <hi>the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the Top of the Mountains, and be exalted above the Hills;</hi> when <hi>he ſhall judge among the Nations, and rebuke many People;</hi> when <hi>the lofty Looks of Men ſhall be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, &amp;c.</hi> And when ſhall this be? It ſhall be <hi>in the laſt Days:</hi> tis yet future: It hath never yet been accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 'Tis call'd <hi>the Day of the Lord, ver.</hi> 12, when <hi>he alone ſhall be exalted;</hi> a Time of Peace when <hi>Nation ſhall not lift up Sword againſt Nation;</hi> no more War then, ver. 4. Tis true, there will be a bloody World <hi>before</hi> this Day comes, and Diſtreſs among Nations foregoing Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. But <hi>afterwards</hi> it will be otherwiſe; when <hi>they ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all God's holy Mountain; for the Earth will be filled with the Knowledge of the Lord,</hi> Chap. 11.9; <hi>the Light of the Moon ſhall be as the Light of the Sun, and the Light of the Sun ſeven-fold,</hi> Chap. 30.26; <hi>no more weeping</hi> then, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. And when ſhall this be? It ſhall be when <hi>Chriſt ſhall reign in Righteouſneſs,</hi> Chap. 32.1; and when <hi>his People ſhall dwell in peaceable Habitations;</hi> when the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be <hi>called,</hi> and the <hi>Saints raiſed,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> and <hi>reign with Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153637:8"/>a Thouſand Years.</hi> Then tis, their <hi>Eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty,</hi> and <hi>ſee Jeruſalem a quiet Habitation,</hi> and <hi>the Lord,</hi> our <hi>Judge,</hi> our <hi>Law-giver, and</hi> our <hi>King, Chap.</hi> 33.17, 20, 22. Then tis, there ſhall be ſuch <hi>Holineſs,</hi> Chap. 35.8; and <hi>everlaſting Joy ſhall be on their Heads, and Sorrow and Sighing ſhall flee away.</hi> Then, and not till then, will God <hi>create new Heavens; Jeruſalem a rejoic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and her People a Joy, Chap.</hi> 65.17, 18, 21. Then ſhall the <hi>build Houſes, and inhabit them; plant Vineyards, and eat the Fruit of them; and long enjoy the Works of their Hands.</hi> None of theſe Things have yet been accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; nor will be till <hi>that wicked be revealed whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroy with the Brightneſs of his Coming,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>Neither can theſe Things be underſtood to be <hi>in</hi> or <hi>after</hi> the <hi>general Judgment.</hi> For then there will be no Building of Houſes, nor planting of Vineyards, nor eating the Fruit of them, nor long enjoying the Labour of their Hands. It muſt be <hi>after</hi> the <hi>Calling</hi> of the <hi>Jews;</hi> this Promiſe having ſpecial Reſpect to them: and therefore all this and much more will be in <hi>the Thouſand Years.</hi> In the <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>which</hi> Chriſt will <hi>come in the Clouds of Heaven</hi> viſibly, as hath been ſhewed before, to judge the Man of Sin, and all other Enemies which ſhall be found in Arms againſt him. And <hi>this Thouſand Years</hi> muſt be placed <hi>between</hi> this Appearance of Chriſt and the general Judgment, which will be after the laſt Reſurrection. But of this more may be ſpoken when we come to ſpeak to the third Queſtion, when this Time ſhall begin. Thoſe alſo that hold that the <hi>general Judgment</hi> will begin at the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> and ſo continue that whole Term of Time, are utterly miſtaken. For beſides what hath been ſaid before as to building and planting; the Scripture is clear, that even then there will be <hi>wicked Men in the World,</hi> tho' they will be <hi>Slaves</hi> as the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were, and chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up as the Devil will be all that while; but at laſt will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153637:9"/>be ſo multiplied that they will be as the Sand of the Sea; and at laſt being deceived by the Devil, when he is let looſe at the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>theſe Thouſand Years,</hi> they will make an Attempt againſt the Saints, to their own Ruin: and that this ſhould be in the Time of the general Judgment, is a Thing not to be believed.</p>
            <p>We have already ſhewed what one Prophet hath ſpoken: but becauſe theſe are the Times of the Reſtitution of all Things ſpoken of by all the holy Prophets which have been ſince the World began; let it be enquired into what <hi>the reſt</hi> of the Prophets have ſpoken.</p>
            <p>JEREM. 3.14, God tells them there that he would <hi>bring them to Sion, and at that Time they ſhould call Jeruſalem the Throne of the Lord, and all Nations ſhould be gathered to it, ver.</hi> 17. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 30.3.9, the Prophet tells them, <hi>the Days ſhould come, that God would bring again the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity both of Iſrael and Judah, and they ſhould ſerve the Lord their God, and David their King. Jer.</hi> 31, the <hi>whole Chap.</hi> throughout ſpeaks fully to the Point in Hand. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet EZEKIEL alſo, <hi>Chap.</hi> 36, tells us of <hi>a Time when God would gather them,</hi> (i. e. the Jews) <hi>out of all Countries, and bring them to their own Land, and cleanſe them from their Filthineſs, pour out his Spirit on them, and they ſhould be his People, and he would be their God:</hi> all which is yet future. Yea the <hi>laſt nine Chapters</hi> ſpeak in a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Way of the State of the Goſpel Church in <hi>the Thouſand Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſee further what DANIEL ſpeaks. He tells us what ſhall be <hi>in the latter Days,</hi> that is <hi>in the latter End of the 4th Kingdom,</hi> viz. the <hi>Roman;</hi> which is now on his laſt <hi>Legs,</hi> if it hath any Leggs left. We are ſure he hath <hi>Feet;</hi> upon which <hi>the Stone cut out of the Mountain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Hand ſhall fall and break the whole Image to Pieces from the Head to the Feet.</hi> Why, <hi>then,</hi> and not till then, <hi>ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdom, which ſhall never be deſtroyed, nor paſs over to another People, but ſtand forever,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153637:9"/>and become a great Mountain and fill the whole Earth:</hi> what elſe is this but <hi>the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe exalted above the Hills?</hi> or <hi>any other Mountain than this,</hi> cannot be meant of a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Kingdom: for that doth not break other Kingdoms to pieces, as <hi>this</hi> doth; and ſuch a Kingdom is not now to be ſet up. But it may be ſaid, what's this to the Point in Hand, viz. to the <hi>Coming of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>the Thouſand Years?</hi> Let us therefore further enquire, and we ſhall ſee that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks up to the Caſe, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.13, 14; <hi>I ſaw,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the Night Viſions, and one like the Son of Man came with the Clouds of Heaven, and came to the antient of Days, and they brought him near before him; and there was given to him Dominion and Glory, and a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that all People Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him; his Dominion is an everlaſting Dominion, that ſhall not paſs away, and his Kingdom that ſhall not be deſtroyed.</hi> But <hi>when</hi> ſhall this Coming of the Son of Man be? It ſhall be <hi>when the little Horn,</hi> viz. the Beaſt <hi>is ſlain, and his Body deſtroyed and given to the burning Flames:</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly with <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20; where tis ſaid, <hi>the Beaſt was taken, and with him the falſe Prophet, and caſt into the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone.</hi> And anſwerable to this is that clear Text, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8, <hi>whom he ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroy with the Brightneſs of his Coming;</hi> which is generally underſtood, eſpecially by the learned, to be a <hi>perſonal</hi> Coming: for ſo much doth the Word in the <hi>original</hi> import; and is no other, than <hi>his Coming with Clouds</hi> above-mentioned; and that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 24, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. And this muſt of Neceſſity be granted; except we ſhall ſay, tis at the <hi>End</hi> of the Thouſand Years (which is not yet begun as may be ſhewed hereafter) when Chriſt comes to the general Judgment; which no Man in his right Underſtanding will affirm: and ſo it will enforce a Coming of Chriſt <hi>perſonally</hi> before the End of the World. And this is further hinted to us, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1; <hi>at that Time</hi> (viz. when the <hi>Turk</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, and come to his End)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153637:10"/>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.45, <hi>ſhall Michael ſtand up, the great Prince which ſtandeth for the Children of thy People;</hi> and <hi>at that Time ſhall they be delivered;</hi> and not long after is <hi>that happy Time, which he is bleſſed that waiteth for it and cometh to it, ver.</hi> 12; which is no other then <hi>the Thouſand Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HOSEA alſo ſpeaks of the ſame Thing, and of the ſame Time above-mentioned, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> when <hi>the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Judah and the Children of Iſrael ſhould be gathered together, and appoint themſelves one Head in that great Day of Jezreel;</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. throughout. JOEL alſo tells us of a Time, when <hi>Jeruſalem ſhould be holy, and no Stranger paſs through her any more, Chap.</hi> 3.17. AMOS alſo ſpeaks of a Day when <hi>God will raiſe up the Tabernacle of David that is fallen, and cloſe up the Breaches thereof, and raiſe up his Ruins, and build it as in the Days of old, Chap.</hi> 9. from <hi>ver.</hi> 11. to the End. OBADIAH alſo to the ſame Purpoſe; that <hi>upon Mount Sion ſhall be Deliverance, and there ſhall be Holineſs, ver.</hi> 17, and <hi>Saviours ſhall come upon Mount Sion, and the Kingdom ſhall be the Lord's.</hi> JONAH is a <hi>Hiſtory, no Propheſy.</hi> MICAH 4.1, 2, 3, but <hi>in the laſt Days, it ſhall come to paſs,</hi>  the ſame with <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2. NAHUM ſpeaks of a Time, when <hi>the Wicked ſhould be among the People of God no more, but be utterly cut off, Chap.</hi> 1.15. HABAKKUK, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.14, <hi>the Earth ſhall be filled with the Knowledge of the Lord as the Waters cover the Sea.</hi> ZEPHANIAH, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.9-20, <hi>I will turn to the People a pure Language, that they may call on the Name of the Lord, and ſerve him with one conſent; in that Day it ſhall be ſaid to Jeruſalem, fear not, and to Sion, let not thy Hands be ſlack, the Lord thy God in the midſt of thee is mighty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>HAGGAI 2.7, The Prophet ſpeaks of a Time when <hi>God would ſhake the Heaven and the Earth, and ſhake all Nations:</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 22, that <hi>he would overthrow the Thrones of Kingdoms, and the Deſire of all Nations ſhould come.</hi> Tis true, this hath been <hi>in Part</hi> fulfilled at the <hi>firſt Coming
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153637:10"/>of Chriſt,</hi> when the legal Diſpenſation was taken away; and ſo much the Apoſtle implies <hi>Heb.</hi> 12: but that Shaking did not overthrow the Thrones of Kingdoms, as this Shak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall. The Apoſtle who wrote after the legal Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation was ſhaken to Pieces, tells us of <hi>another Shaking</hi> which God had promiſed, which was future. And <hi>when</hi> may this be? It may be 'tis <hi>when</hi> the Deſire of all Nations ſhall come the <hi>ſecond Time,</hi> to ſit up his own Kingdom; <hi>then</hi> when <hi>the Beaſt ſhall be ſlain, and his Body deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and given to the burning Flames;</hi> when <hi>the Ancient of Days ſhall ſit; then,</hi> and not 'till then, will <hi>theſe Thrones be caſt down, Dan.</hi> 7.9. And that Time will be a ſhaking Time indeed; when not only the <hi>Earth,</hi> but the <hi>Power of Heaven</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſhaken</hi> alſo; <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. And <hi>theſe Heavens and Earth</hi> ſo ſhaken muſt be <hi>removed;</hi> and <hi>a new Heaven and Earth created that ſhall remain before the Lord, Iſai.</hi> 66.22. And ſo the Apoſtle tells us <hi>Heb.</hi> 12, of <hi>a Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken;</hi> by which we muſt underſtand <hi>the whole</hi> Kingdom of Chriſt, and not only <hi>his ſpiritual</hi> Kingdom, but his external alſo, <hi>which he is gone to receive;</hi> which is <hi>an ever laſting Kingdom, and ſhall never paſs away to another People;</hi> which muſt remain when thoſe Things that are ſhaken muſt be removed.</p>
            <p>See alſo what the Prophet ZECHARIAH ſpeaks <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.3, <hi>The Lord ſaith, I am returned to Sion, and will dwell in the midſt of Jeruſalem; and Jeruſalem ſhall be called a City of Truth, the Mountain of the Lord of Hoſts, the holy Mountain.</hi> See <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8; &amp; <hi>Chap.</hi> 12, 13, 14. The Prophet ſpeaks of little elſe, but the Glory and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, after their Converſion to Chriſt. There is yet one Prophet more who is yet to ſpeak, and that is MALACHI; and he ſpeaks of <hi>the Day of the Lord that ſhall burn as an Oven; and all that do Wickedly ſhall be ſtubble, and the Day that cometh ſhall burn them up; and ye ſhall tread them down, for they ſhall be Aſhes under the Soles of your Feet.</hi> But it may be thought that this Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153637:11"/>ſhall be at the <hi>laſt Judgment.</hi> Tis true, there will then be the greateſt Deſtruction by Fire that ever was or ſhall be; for then they will be deſtroyed all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9: but tis likely, it will be otherwiſe now, conſiſting only of ſuch as are actually in Arms againſt Chriſt. But that there will be a great Deſtruction <hi>by Fire</hi> at this Time, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is clear, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.15.16, <hi>For behold the Lord will come with Fire, and render his Rebukes with Flames of Fire; for by Fire and Sword will be Lord plead with all Fleſh, and the Slain of the Lord ſhall be many.</hi> See <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 38.22, Words to the ſame Purpoſe. And when <hi>this Burning</hi> ſhall be, <hi>the Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhall ariſe with healing in his Wings; and his People ſhall go forth, and grow up as Calves of the Stall:</hi> and when <hi>the Hearts of the Children ſhould be turned to their Fathers;</hi> what elſe is here meant but the Converſion of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation; that they ſhould be turned to ſerve the God whom their Fathers ſerved: which will be long before the End of the World.</p>
            <p>I might weary the Reader with Quotations; but have only ſingled out ſome among many, whereby it doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear, that the TIME of THE RESTITUTION OF ALL THINGS ſpoken of <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21, cannot be meant of the <hi>laſt Judgment:</hi> for that is not the Time of the Reſtitution of all Things ſpoken off by all the holy Prophets; but the Annihilation of many Things: Neither have <hi>all the Prophets</hi> ſpoken of <hi>the laſt Judgment;</hi> nor any one of them who have been mentioned, that I know of; neither ever is <hi>the laſt Judgment</hi> repreſented to us, by <hi>Times</hi> as I remember; but always by a <hi>Day,</hi> the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> the <hi>Day of the Lord.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16; <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31; <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.22; and 12.36; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10, and elſewhere; and therefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe is meant by RESTITUTION OF ALL THINGS; which we ſhall next enquire into.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſtitution</hi> in the original ſignifieth, the ſetting of a Thing in his right and ancient State; as is well known to ſome: and the ſame Word with that <hi>Act.</hi> 1.6. To <hi>Reſtore</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153637:11"/>by <hi>Reſtitution of all Things,</hi> may in general mean a new State of Things in this World: and more eſpecially the Converſion or Reſtoration of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation to the Love and Favour of God; to be again the Church and People of God; to reſtore them to their own Land; to reſtore the Kingdom to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> to reſtore their Judges as at the firſt, and their Counſellors as at the beginning, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1; to reſtore Comfort to them and their Mourners; to reſtore Joy and Sorrow; and Sighing flee away, <hi>Chap.</hi> 35; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Peace like a River; ſee for this <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.12, 13; and 57.18, 19. Theſe Things have been ſpoken of <hi>by all the holy Prophets,</hi> as hath been largely ſhewed before; and are no other then the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>the Reſtitution of all Things,</hi> and <hi>the Thouſand Years.</hi> Then the Enmity of the Creature ſhall ceaſe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.18; <hi>they ſhall not deſtroy nor hurt in all God's holy Mountain, Iſai.</hi> 11.9: then ſhall Enemies be deſtroyed, ſo as not to perſecute any more; ſo that it may well be called a Time of <hi>the Reſtitution of all Things,</hi> and <hi>Times of refreſhing from the Preſence of the Lord:</hi> for then, <hi>their Sins ſhall be blotted out; ſo that tho' they ſhould be ſought for, they ſhall not be found.</hi> And this will be <hi>a Time of Refreſhing,</hi> not only to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, but to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo; for <hi>the renewing</hi> of <hi>then</hi> will be <hi>as Life from the Dead to the Gentiles.</hi> Now all this, and much more which might be mentioned, hath never yet been accompliſhed; nor ſhall be, till the grand Enemies of Chriſt be deſtroyed, and <hi>the third-Wo Trumpet ſound.</hi> And that the Time of the Reſtitution of all Things ſhould be <hi>after</hi> the general Judgment is began, is to me incredible; and therefore it will neceſſarily follow, that <hi>theſe Times of the Reſtitution of all Things,</hi> is a Term of Time <hi>between</hi> the <hi>third-Wo Trumpet</hi> and the <hi>general Judgment.</hi> And what Time may we think it to be but <hi>the Thouſand Years</hi> of Chriſt's Kingdom in this World; which will commence im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Deſtruction of his Enemies, and the Calling of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and continue till the <hi>General Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153637:12"/>and at this Time of Reſtitution it is, that <hi>Chriſt will come,</hi> Act. 3.21, <hi>and deſtroy the Man of</hi> Sin, <hi>with the Brightneſs of his Coming:</hi> except we ſhould ſay, that the ſhould not be deſtroyed till the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> or <hi>general Judgment;</hi> which I think no Man of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding will affirm.</p>
            <p>But it may be thought that <hi>theſe Thouſand Years</hi> are <hi>paſt</hi> long ago. That is then the</p>
            <p n="2">II. Thing to be enquired into. And here we muſt know, (1) that <hi>theſe Thouſand Years cannot be in any Part</hi> of the <hi>Reign</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> and (2dly) that <hi>in the Space of theſe Thouſand Years Satan muſt be bound, and ſhut up in the bottomleſs Pit:</hi> Both theſe muſt be granted. Thoſe then that affirm that theſe Years are <hi>Paſt,</hi> let them begin them when they will; will have a Part of the Reign of the Beaſt included in them.</p>
            <p>Again, we find, that in the <hi>beginning</hi> of the Thouſand Years, <hi>thoſe that ſuffered under the Beaſt</hi> were to be <hi>raiſed</hi> and <hi>reign with Chriſt,</hi> Rev. 20; and 'tis abſurd to ſay, that any of the raiſed Saints that were to reign with Chriſt, ſhould ſuffer <hi>after their Reſurrection,</hi> and in the Time of their Reign: Their <hi>Sufferings</hi> muſt go <hi>before</hi> their <hi>Reigning;</hi> according to that of the Apoſtle 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12; &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17; which is not a reigning in Heaven, as poſſibly may be hereafter ſhown. Nor <hi>hath Satan hitherto been bound;</hi> and this Thouſand Years are <hi>not</hi> to <hi>begin,</hi> 'till <hi>Satan be bound</hi> from deceiving the Nations. Now Satan hath hitherto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Nations in all Ages and Generations, in Doctrine, by Paganiſm, Arianiſm; and to this Day doth, by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther damnable Hereſies: And can we ſuppoſe that he <hi>hath been,</hi> or <hi>now</hi> is <hi>bound?</hi> What may we think he will do then when he is <hi>looſe?</hi> And therefore this Thouſand Years and Kingdom of Chriſt is not yet begun; becauſe no Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration have ever yet been ſo happy as to be free from his Deceptions in one Way or other. By this then which hath been ſpoken, it may appear to any, who will not wilfully ſhut their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153637:12"/>Eyes, that the Thouſand Years of Satans binding and the Saints reigning are yet future; and therefore we ſhall inſiſt no further upon it; but come to the,</p>
            <p n="3">IIId. Thing to be ſpoken to, as was propoſed; that is <hi>from what Period of Time it doth begin.</hi> To anſwer in general, This Thouſand Years <hi>begins</hi> when Chriſt comes to ſet up his Kingdom in this world. And here we muſt know, That <hi>of that Day and Hour, no nor Year,</hi> when Chriſt will come to ſet up his Kingdom, Chriſt hath told us, <hi>no Man knoweth, no not the Angels,</hi> Matth. 24: And when the Diſciples (<hi>Acts</hi> 1.) would needs know, whether <hi>at that Time</hi> Chriſt would ſet up his Kingdom, or reſtore the Kingdom to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Chriſt doth not deny the Thing, which doubtleſs he would have done if there had been no ſuch Thing, and have rectifyed their Judgments, and informed them better: but otherwiſe he only checks their Curioſity, and tells them, 'twas not for them to know <hi>the Times and Seaſons</hi> which the Father hath put in his own Power: And <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.20, when the Phariſees demanded and would know of Chriſt. <hi>when the Kingdom of Chriſt ſhould come?</hi> he tells them, <hi>if came not with Obſervation; neither ſhould Men ſay, Lo here, or lo there;</hi> but he would <hi>come as Lightning,</hi> ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, terribly; <hi>ſo ſhall alſo the Son of Man be in his Day:</hi> and goes on to give them ſome <hi>general Signs,</hi> as <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Senſuality;</hi> as it was <hi>in the Days</hi> of <hi>Noah;</hi> and as it was <hi>in the Days</hi> of <hi>Lott; Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking, Marrying, Building</hi> and <hi>planting,</hi>  and <hi>knew nothing 'till the Flood came;</hi> even <hi>thus ſhall it be when the Son of Man ſhull be revealed,</hi> ver. 26, 27, 30. And Luk. 19.11, <hi>There were ſome that thought that the Kingdom of God ſhould imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately appear;</hi> but Chriſt gives them to underſtand otherwiſe; and repreſents himſelf as <hi>a certain noble Man that went into a far Country, to receive for himſelf a Kingdom and to return:</hi> And <hi>ver</hi> 15, when he was returned, having receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Kingdom, then he calls his Servants to account, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153637:13"/>paſſes Sentence on them. Hence he is ſaid to <hi>judge quick and dead at his Appearance and his Kingdom,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1. And therefore when he <hi>come to ſet up his Kingdom</hi> at <hi>the Sounding</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Trumpet;</hi> at the Time he is ſaid to <hi>Judge and to give Rewards to his Servants,</hi> Rev. 11, 15, 18. So that at <hi>his Return</hi> will be the <hi>Time when</hi> this Kingdom of Chriſt ſhall <hi>appear,</hi> and the Thouſand Years <hi>begin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to enquire a little further concerning THE TIME, and ſee what the Scripture ſpeaks to it: and we ſhall find, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.5, 6, 7; that <hi>under the ſixth Trumpet, which is the ſecond Woe Trumpet,</hi> Chap. 9.12; the <hi>Angel,</hi> which is CHRIST, <hi>who ſets his right Foot on the Sea, &amp; his left Foot on the Earth, and lifteth up his Hand to Heaven, and ſweareth by him that liveth for ever and ever, that there ſhould be Time no longer;</hi> but <hi>in the Days of the Voice of the ſeventh Angel,</hi> when he ſhall <hi>begin</hi> to ſound, <hi>the Myſtery of God ſhould be finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as he hath declared to his Servants the Prophets.</hi> What, Should the World be now at an End, that Time ſhould be no longer; <hi>when the ſeventh Angel ſounded?</hi> No, not ſo; but then <hi>Time</hi> ſhould be <hi>no longer to the Beaſt and other Enemies of Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>then</hi> the <hi>Myſtery of God ſhould be finiſhed.</hi> But <hi>what may this Myſtery,</hi> which muſt be finiſhed <hi>after the Sound of the ſeventh Trumpet, be?</hi> which is the <hi>laſt Trumpet;</hi> after which none ſhall Sound, but <hi>the Trump of God</hi> at <hi>the laſt Judgment,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.52; at the Reſurrection of the Dead; And this the Apoſtle calls <hi>a Myſtery:</hi> but this is <hi>not</hi> the Myſtery of God <hi>here meant;</hi> for God had not declared this to his Servants the Prophets: Much leſs is it the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.7; for <hi>that</hi> is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Myſtery of God,</hi> but of the <hi>Devil.</hi> There is yet <hi>another Myſtery</hi> of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks Rev. 11.25; and that is <hi>the Calling of the Jews:</hi> And <hi>this Myſtery hath been declared to all the Prophets,</hi> as hath been ſhewed before: And <hi>this Myſtery of God</hi> is to be <hi>finiſhed under the ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> and at the <hi>pouring out of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153637:13"/>laſt Vial:</hi> For then 'tis ſaid, <hi>It is done.</hi> What is that which is done? Then <hi>the Myſtery of Gods is fulfilled,</hi> Chap. 10.7: And at the <hi>pouring out of this Vial,</hi> which is <hi>contempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> with the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> there <hi>will be Voices, and Thunderings, and Lightnings,</hi> to ſtrike Terror into the Minds of Men, and there <hi>will be a great Earthquake— ſuch as was not ſince Men were upon the Earth, ſo mighty and Earthquake, and ſo great:</hi> It will ſhake all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World; ſhake the Heavens, and ſhake the Earth; the Lord will ſhake all the World by it; and Things ſo ſhaken muſt be removed, that what cannot be ſhaken may remain: but of his ſomething hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before. But what may <hi>this Earthquake be,</hi> which ſhall thus ſhake the whole World, and ſuch as never was ſince Men lived upon Earth? I do <hi>not</hi> underſtand it of an Earthquake <hi>properly</hi> ſo called: but ſo as it repreſents to us great Changes in the World, and <hi>Diſtreſe of Nations, with Perplexity, Mens Hearts failing them for Fear, and for looking after thoſe Things which are coming on the Earth: For the Powers of Heaven ſhall be ſhaken,</hi> Luk. 21.25, 26. We read of a <hi>great Earthquake</hi> Rev. 6, at the <hi>Opening of the ſixth Seal:</hi> And it was ſo great, that it ſhook the <hi>Pagan Roman Empire;</hi> for ſo Interpretors un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that Place; the <hi>whole Pagan Emperial World,</hi> Sun, Moon, and Stars thereof: and this introduced a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Change for the preſent. So that we ſee ſuch Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes ſignify great Changes, and affrighting Judgments, by Wars, and otherwiſe: and ſuch will be at <hi>the Sounding of the ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> and the <hi>pouring out of the laſt Vial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.14, we read of <hi>the Kings of the Earth, and of the whole World gathered together, to the</hi> BATTLE <hi>of the</hi> GREAT DAY <hi>of</hi> GOD ALMIGHTY: And it is the <hi>ſame</hi> Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Chap. 38. &amp; 39; for that was to be <hi>in the latter Day,</hi> ver. 16: And it muſt be <hi>at,</hi> or <hi>after,</hi> the <hi>return</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>their own Land;</hi> which is yet future. And the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> alſo ſpeaks of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153637:14"/>
               <hi>ſame</hi> Battle <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.2. <hi>For behold in thoſe Days and in that Time, when I ſhall bring again the Captivity of</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>I will gather all Nations, and bring them down to the Valley of</hi> Jehoſhaphat, <hi>and plead with them there.</hi> A more general War-like Aſſembly was never known in the World: and by Means whereof, there will be ſuch an Earthquake as was never heard of ſince the World began: And this will be all at the <hi>ſame Time,</hi> 'the <hi>Calling</hi> of the <hi>Jews;</hi> at the <hi>ſame Place</hi> Judea; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.4, <hi>upon the Mountains of</hi> Iſrael; Joel 3.2. <hi>in the Valley of</hi> Jehoſhaphat; Rev. 16.16. <hi>at</hi> Armageddon. To this Time the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> refers <hi>Chap.</hi> 63.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. where Chriſt is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as <hi>treading the Wine-preſs, treading</hi> his <hi>Enemies in Anger, trampling on them in Fury, Garments ſtained with their Blood:</hi> Juſt the <hi>ſame</hi> with Rev. 14.15, 20. <hi>Thruſt in thy Sickle into the Earth, and gather the Vine of the Earth: and the Angel thruſt in his Sickle, and gathered the Vine of the Earth, and caſt in into the great Wine-preſs of the Wrath of God.</hi> But more of this, when we come to ſpeak of the <hi>great Battle</hi> of GOD and MAGOG. <hi>Joel</hi> alſo ſpeaks to the <hi>ſame Purpoſe</hi> and the <hi>ſame Time;</hi> then <hi>will Men go into the Clefts of the Rocks, and into the Tops of the ragged Rocks, for Fear of the Lord, and for the Glory of his Majeſty, when he ariſeth terribly to ſhake the Earth;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this little above-written, we may partly judge what <hi>this Earthquake</hi> is like to be; and to do which is ſo great as was not ſince Men lived upon Earth: For <hi>now the old World will be at an End,</hi> and <hi>the new World will begin;</hi> which the Apoſtle calls <hi>the World to come,</hi> Heb. 2.5. Thus much may ſuffice for <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>third Queſtion,</hi> propoſed to be ſpoken to, i.e. <hi>when</hi> the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> will <hi>begin,</hi> and all the Kingdoms of this World become the Kingdoms of our Lord and his Chriſt, and he to reign for ever and ever. And this is one of the moſt remarkable Periods which hath been ſince the World began.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153637:14"/>
            <p>Concerning <hi>the glorious State of this Kingdom of Chriſt in this World,</hi> ſomething hath been hinted before, which may be further evinced from the Scriptures. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to <hi>a plentiful Effuſion of the</hi> SPIRIT, promiſed; that it ſhall be poured out from on high, <hi>when the Wilderneſs ſhall become a fruitful Field,</hi> Iſa. 32.15; which is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of great Meaſures and Degrees of all ſaving Grace: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed alſo <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. to be <hi>poured out upon the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and upon the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem: But <hi>when</hi> is it? <hi>when they ſhall look non him whom they have pierced and mourn.</hi> Alſo <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 36.27, <hi>I will put my Spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, and cauſe you to walk in my Statutes:</hi> But <hi>when? When they are gathered out of all Countries, and brought to their own Land,</hi> ver. 24.</p>
            <p>And this will not only be (1.) a Spirit of LIGHT and KNOWLEDGE; but (2) there will be <hi>much</hi> HOLINESS: It will be to ſuch a Degree as never was in the World ſince the Beginning of it: So great, that ſome Men have thought, (though I am not of that Opinion) that there will be no Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holineſs (at leaſt) not in the Saints; but that the Subjects of this Kingdom ſhall ſin no more. See further what the Scripture ſpeaks to this, Iſa. 35.8, <hi>An high Way ſhall be there: And it ſhall be called the Way of Holineſs: The Unclean ſhall not paſs over it.</hi> Hence called <hi>God's holy Mountain, Iſai.</hi> 65. <hi>ult; the Mountain of his Holineſs, Jer.</hi> 32.23: Upon the Bells of Horſes and Pots ſhall be <hi>Holineſs, Zech.</hi> 14.20. (3dly) As to RIGHTEOUSNESS; <hi>the People ſhall be all Righteous: they ſhall inherit the Land forever, Iſai.</hi> 35.8. Hence they are called <hi>a righteous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Chap.</hi> 26.2; <hi>The Habitation of Juſtice, Jer.</hi> 31.23.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Righteouſneſs aud</hi> PEACE <hi>will kiſs each other, Pſa.</hi> 85; which is next propoſed to Conſideration. For CHRIST being <hi>the Prince of Peace, Iſa.</hi> 9.6; there ſhall be Peace in his Kingdom, and under his Government. <hi>The Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſhall bring Peace to his People, Pſal.</hi> 72.3: <hi>In his Days ſhall be abundance of Peace, ſo long as the Moon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153637:15"/>ver.</hi> 7: and I am ſure that will be <hi>to the End</hi> of <hi>the Thouſand Years.</hi> Again, <hi>Great ſhall be the Peace of thy Children, Iſa.</hi> 54.13; <hi>Peace to him that is far off, and Peace to him that is near, Chap.</hi> 57.19; <hi>Peace like a River:</hi> A Succeſſion of Peace, as of Waters in a River: <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſhall be a quiet Habitation, and a peaceable reſting Place, Iſa.</hi> 32.18; &amp; 33.20, <hi>They ſhall not learn War any more; nor any Weapon that is formed againſt them ſhall proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, there will be JOY: when <hi>the Lord reigneth, the Earth will rejoice, Pſal.</hi> 97.1; and <hi>ver.</hi> 8, <hi>Sion heard, and was glad, and the Daughters of Judah rejoiced: ſing for Joy of Heart, Iſai.</hi> 65.14, <hi>rejoice with Joy and Singing; everlaſting Joy will be upon their Heads; and they ſhall obtain Joy and Gladneſs; and Sorrow and Sighing ſhall flee away.</hi> Therefore in this Kingdom of Chriſt, during <hi>the Thouſand Years,</hi> there will be no more Apoſtacy or Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding in Holineſs; or as it was in the Days of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> when the World was filled with Violence, and all Fleſh had corrupted their Way. Neither is there the leaſt Hint in Scripture of any Backſliding <hi>after</hi> this Thouſand Years is begun. For then there could not be <hi>everlaſting Joy on their Heads,</hi> nor could Sorrow and Sighing flee away. No more <hi>pricking Briar, nor grieving Thorn:</hi> no more Perſecution by wicked Men: no more <hi>violent Death, nor Sorrow, nor Crying, nor any more Pain,</hi> upon any ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; For then Sorrow and Sighing would not flee away, nor would Tears be wiped from their Eyes. We may further take notice that this Time will be a Time of <hi>great</hi> LIGHT. <hi>The Earth ſhall be filled with the Knowledge of the Lord as the Waters cover the Sea: The Light of the Moon ſhall be as the Light of the Sun; And the Light of the Sun as the Light of ſeven Days: At the Time of the End Knowledge ſhall be increaſed, Dan.</hi> 12.4.</p>
            <p>Then there will be a <hi>glorious Accompliſhment of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions</hi> and Propheſies, which now to us are dark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure: and the Book which is now ſealed at the Time of the End, will be opened.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153637:15"/>
            <p>Much more might be added to what hath been written; but we ſhall at preſent give ſome Scriptures which ſpeak of this EXTERNAL AND OUTWARD HAPPINESS. Firſt, <hi>long Life; Iſai.</hi> 65, <hi>there ſhall be no more thence an infant of Days, nor an old Man that hath not filled his Days; for the Child ſhall die an Hundred Years old; for as the Days of a Tree, are the Days of my People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, they ſhall enjoy <hi>a Fulneſs of other temporal Bleſſings; build Houſes, plant Vineyards, and eat the Fruit of them, Iſai.</hi> 65. <hi>Their Floors ſhall be full of Wheat, and the Fats ſhall overflow with Wine and Oyl; and they ſhall eat in plenty, and praiſe the Name of the Lord, that hath dealt wonderfully with them; and they ſhall never be aſhamed, Joel</hi> 2. Then will be fulfilled, according to the Letter ſpoken by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.5, <hi>Bleſſed are the Meek for they ſhall inherit the Earth:</hi> which hitherto they have not done. Oh, <hi>glorious Things are ſpoken of thee, O City of God, Selah,</hi> Pſal. 87, 3. <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed in the City of our God, in the Mountain of Holineſs, beautiful for Situation, the Joy of the whole Earth, the City of the great King, Pſal.</hi> 48.1, 2: which Places ultimately refer to this Time, and the glorious State of the Church in the laſt Age of the World.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church of old</hi> was called, <hi>the Lord's Portion, Deut.</hi> 32.9; <hi>his pleaſant Portion,</hi> Jer. 12.10; <hi>his Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,</hi> Iſai. 19.25; and <hi>the dearly beloved of his Soul; his Treaſure,</hi> Exod. 19.5; <hi>his Glory,</hi> Iſai. 46.13. But the <hi>Goſpel Church</hi> is call'd <hi>a Crown of Glory,</hi> Iſai. 62.3; <hi>the Houſe of his Glory, a royal Diadem.</hi> Theſe are high Expreſſes of the Glory of the Church in the Thouſand Years of Chriſt's Kingdom in this World.</p>
            <p>And thus, I have written a little, and but a little; may ſee a Glimpſe, and but a Glimpſe, of Sions Glory; much of which is yet to come. And from all that which is here written we may gather, that if <hi>the Times immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding</hi> the <hi>perſonal,</hi> viſible and glorious Appearance of Chriſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153637:16"/>at his <hi>ſecond Coming,</hi> be Times of deep Security, general Senſuality, open Prophaneſs and Apoſtacy, as hath been declared before; then it muſt needs be, that <hi>Chriſt will appear before</hi> the <hi>Thouſand Years:</hi> becauſe after thoſe Years are began, there will be no ſuch Times of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Prophaneſs, as hath been alſo ſhewed before: but the <hi>firſt</hi> is undeniable; and therefore the <hi>ſecond</hi> muſt and will neceſſarily follow: for it cannot be imagined, by any that know or underſtand any Thing, of the glorious State of the Church during that Time, which hath been mentioned before, and which hath been ſo abundantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared both by the Prophets and Apoſtles, ſhould ever apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatize ſo as to be as it was <hi>in the Days</hi> of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lott,</hi> when the whole World was corrupt &amp; fill'd with Violence Read their woful Wickedneſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. &amp; 19; and then conſider if ever there will be ſuch Wickedneſs committed <hi>during the Thouſand Years</hi> of Chriſt Kingdom in this World: and there is not the leaſt Hint of declining: and if not, then it will be a Truth that Chriſt will come <hi>before</hi> that Time.</p>
            <p>And now having written ſomething of <hi>Chriſt's Coming,</hi> and of the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of it, and of the <hi>Signs</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going it; in further Proſecution thereof, we ſhall propound <hi>ſeveral Scriptures</hi> to Conſideration, and then as God ſhall help, write ſomething of the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body</hi> and of <hi>Judgment to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us conſider of ſuch <hi>Scriptures</hi> as ſpeak of this Coming of Chriſt. We have formerly ſpoken of <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10; <hi>they ſhall look on him whom they,</hi> i. e. the elect <hi>Jews,</hi> look on Chriſt whom they in their Fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>pierced and mourn for him, as one for an only Son;</hi> with a great and general Mourning; Lands mourn, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies mourn apart: Propheſied of <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.19, by <hi>ſmiting on the Thigh, and by being aſhamed and confounded.</hi> And this is not a deſperate, but a <hi>penitential</hi> Mourning; as is evident:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153637:16"/>For 'tis <hi>when the Spirit of Grace and Supplication</hi> is <hi>poured out upon them;</hi> and <hi>when a Fountain</hi> is <hi>opened for them for Sin and for Uncleanneſs.</hi> Nor can this be referred to the general Judgment; for then will be no ſuch Fountain opened; then twill be too late to repent. And this muſt be underſtood of a <hi>perſonal</hi> Appearance: how elſe ſhould they look on him? <hi>they ſhall ſee the Son of Man Coming in the Clouds of Heaven, Mat.</hi> 24.21; 26.64: that is, not with an Eye of Faith; for that is the Evidence of Things not ſeen; but with their bodily Eyes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7; <hi>behold he cometh with Clouds, and every Eye ſhall ſee him;</hi> (whether they have Faith or no) <hi>and they alſo that have pierced him.</hi> And who can tell but this might be <hi>one</hi> Reaſon why Chriſt was peirced, that the Jews might be convinced and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted at the Sight thereof. See <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.4, <hi>his Feet ſhall ſtand at that Day upon the Mount of Olives:</hi> In what Day? Why tis in the Day <hi>when Chriſt ſhall come and all his Saints with him, ver.</hi> 5; and <hi>when the Jews ſhall ſee him and mourn.</hi> It was from this Mount he aſcended; and ſo he was to come again in like Manner, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. And doubtleſs the <hi>Place</hi> to which Chriſt comes, will be in <hi>Judea;</hi> and at or near <hi>Jeruſalem, where all Nations ſhall be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together to Battle, Chap.</hi> 14.2.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture is <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. ult, <hi>Ye ſhall not henceforth ſee me until ye ſhall ſay bleſſed is he that cometh to us in the Name of the Lord:</hi> then they ſhall cry as the Multitude did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21, <hi>Hoſanna in the higheſt,</hi> i. e. acknowledge Chriſt to be the Meſſiah, and be converted: whereby we may gather, that then they ſhall ſee him. And in <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21; <hi>whom the Heavens muſt</hi> contain or <hi>receive until the Times of the Reſtitution of all Things:</hi> and then <hi>God would ſend Jeſus;</hi> but of this before. Like unto this is that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1, <hi>Sit thou at my right Hand till I make thine Enemies thy Footſtool:</hi> implying, that then Chriſt ſhould ſet at the Fathers right Hand no longer; and all this before the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Judgment. Again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.16; <hi>when the Lord ſhall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153637:17"/>build up Sion, he ſhall appear in his Glory:</hi> then he will <hi>hear the Groans of the poor Priſoners,</hi> and <hi>proclaim Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Captives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Scripture is 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8; 'tis ſaid there that <hi>Chriſt ſhall deſtroy the Man of Sin with the Brightneſs of his Coming,</hi> or appearing, i. e. a <hi>perſonal</hi> Appearing: the Word <hi>Epiphania</hi> imports a <hi>perſonal Appearance:</hi> And Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>come down from Heaven,</hi> to <hi>bind Satan,</hi> at the <hi>Beginning</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> and <hi>the Beaſt</hi> was to be <hi>deſtroyed</hi> before that Time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20, and <hi>caſt alive into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall inſtance only in one Scripture more; and that is in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28; 'tis ſaid there that <hi>Chriſt ſhall appear the ſecond Time without Sin to them that look for him, to their Salvation.</hi> Whether all that ſhall be ſaved by him look for his Appearance, or whether he will appear to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any other the ſecond Time; I ſhall not determine: Only this, that, <hi>in an Hour when good Servants think not of, the Son of Man comes, Matt.</hi> 24.44; and to the <hi>evil Servant in a Day when he looked not for him, ver.</hi> 50: I ſhall ſpeak only to the <hi>Time.</hi> But it may be tho't, that this Text makes againſt ſuch as hold that Chriſt will come before the general Judgment: And it may be not. I know that moſt Men, who underſtand any Thing of theſe Matters, do underſtand, and that rightly, that this Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance the <hi>ſecond Time</hi> is a <hi>perſonal</hi> Appearance of Chriſt; but think that 'tis at the laſt Judgment. But that is their Miſtake; for the Apoſtle knew well, that the <hi>ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of Chriſt would be <hi>to deſtroy the Man of Sin</hi> and <hi>other Enemies,</hi> and that long before the laſt Day, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7; and had told the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> ſo; and had told the <hi>Romans</hi> what <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had ſpoken, <hi>Chap.</hi> 59.20, that <hi>the Redeemer ſhould come to Sion, to them that turn from Tranſgreſſion in</hi> Jacob, and applies it to the <hi>Converſion of the Jews, Rom.</hi> 11.26: and he knew it would be at his <hi>ſecond Coming,</hi> out of <hi>Zec.</hi> 12.10, &amp; <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.30, long before the End of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153637:17"/>World: and therefore <hi>did not mean</hi> the <hi>laſt Judgment</hi> in this Place. And whereas 'tis ſaid, <hi>he ſhall come the ſecond Time without Sin to our Salvation;</hi> we know, or may know, that <hi>Salvation</hi> in Scripture is taken more Ways than one. There is a <hi>temporal</hi> Salvation, as well as a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and an <hi>eternal</hi> Salvation: and 'tis a <hi>temporal</hi> Salvation intended in this Text; as I underſtand, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.71; Chriſt was to <hi>ſave his People from their Enemies, and from the Hands of all that hate them; that we being delivered out of the Hands of our Enemies, might ſerve him without Fear.</hi> And indeed <hi>the great Work</hi> and Buſineſs that Chriſt hath to do in this World, at his next or <hi>ſecond Coming,</hi> will be <hi>to deſtroy his Enemies;</hi> and to <hi>deliver his People, that they may ſerve him without Fear,</hi> which hitherto they could never do; therefore 'tis ſaid, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6.7, <hi>'Tis a righteous Thing with God to recompence Tribulation to them that trouble you; and to you who are troubled Reſt,</hi> or <hi>Refreſhing,</hi> as the Word may be rendered: But when? this hath never yet been, no; but it ſhall be at his <hi>ſecond</hi> or <hi>next Coming, when he ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels,</hi> and <hi>when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, ver.</hi> 10. And 'tis likely theſe are thoſe <hi>Times of Refreſhing, which ſhall come from the Preſence of the Lord;</hi> and <hi>that Reſt</hi> mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 4, that is <hi>remaining</hi> to the Saints and <hi>People of God.</hi> When Perſecution ceaſed, <hi>the Churches had Reſt, Act.</hi> 9.31.</p>
            <p>Much more might be written to ſhow, that the <hi>next</hi> or <hi>ſecond</hi> Coming of Chriſt will be long before the <hi>general</hi> Judgment; but let this ſuffice. And now let us conſider further, <hi>what Chriſt will do</hi> at <hi>this his next Coming.</hi> He will appear <hi>perſonally</hi> and viſibly, as hath been ſhewed: And as he went, <hi>Act.</hi> 1; he will come with the ſame Glory, as when he comes to the general Judgment; ſitting on a Throne as a King: And he <hi>comes with Ten Thouſand of his Saints, Jud.</hi> 14; <hi>comes and all his Saints with him, Zec.</hi> 12. And the <hi>firſt Thing</hi> that Chriſt will do when he comes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153637:18"/>he will <hi>raiſe up the dead Saints,</hi> or ſome of them; and this is called <hi>the firſt Reſurrection, Rev.</hi> 20.4. And here we muſt know, that there is a <hi>firſt Reſurrection,</hi> and there is a <hi>laſt Reſurrection;</hi> and that there is a <hi>firſt</hi> or <hi>inchoate Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and there is a <hi>laſt</hi> or <hi>ultimate Judgment,</hi> which the Scripture ſpeaks of: and it will fall in naturally to ſpeak of them both together. And the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing largely of the Reſurrection, doth imply a priority and a poſteriority of the Reſurrection, <hi>ver.</hi> 23; where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Chriſt the firſt Fruit, afterwards they that are Chriſt's at his Coming.</hi> But what Coming? to the <hi>general Judgment?</hi> No, but <hi>long before</hi> that Time: For at the general Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not only <hi>them that are Chriſt's</hi> ſhall be raiſed; but <hi>all that are in Graves, ſmall and great, all that are in the Sea,</hi> or <hi>in Hell; all muſt appear before his judgment-Seat,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, the <hi>Bad</hi> as well as <hi>Good:</hi> and therefore there is a Reſurrection of <hi>ſome</hi> before that Time. Beſides, the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>every one ſhould be made alive in his own Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; Chriſt</hi> was <hi>the firſt Fruit</hi> above 1600 Years ago, <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards</hi> will be the <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>ſome of them</hi> at <hi>his Coming;</hi> AFTERWARDS, (for ſo is the Word in the Original, as I have been informed,) <hi>cometh the End.</hi> What End? Not only the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> but the <hi>End of the World,</hi> as to the preſent State of it; and then, as I conceive, will be the <hi>laſt Reſurrection</hi> and the <hi>general Judgment:</hi> After the End of which <hi>the Kingdom ſhall be delivered to God even the Father, and God ſhall be all in all.</hi> The <hi>Sum</hi> is, that as there is a <hi>long intervall</hi> of Time between the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>thoſe that are Chriſt's at his Coming;</hi> ſo more than a few Hours or Years will be between the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>theſe,</hi> and the <hi>laſt Reſurrection:</hi> and ſo much doth the Word <hi>[Order]</hi> import and imply a Diſtance of Time; there being no mention made that I know of, of any Riſing of any at Chriſt's ſecond Coming but of <hi>thoſe that are his:</hi> And if this be not the Meaning of this Scripture, I know not what is.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:153637:18"/>
            <p>The <hi>next Scripture</hi> we ſhall mention to this Purpoſe is, that ſo much controverted Place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, <hi>John</hi> in a Viſion <hi>ſaw the Souls of them that were beheeded for the Witneſs of Jeſus, and for the Word of God, and which had not worſhipped the Beaſt nor his Image, nor received his Mark in their Foreheads, or in their Hands; and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a Thouſand Years; but the</hi> REST <hi>of the Dead lived not again till the Thouſand Years were finiſhed.</hi> So that tis plain by this Text, that <hi>ſome</hi> ſhall <hi>riſe a Thouſand Years before others:</hi> and that is here called <hi>the firſt Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe moſt Men think that this is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a <hi>bodily</hi> Reſurrection, but of a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Regeneration;</hi> let us enquire what the Scripture ſaith to this Point, and what may be ſaid in Anſwer to thoſe that are of that Opinion. And here, tis readily granted, that <hi>Regeneration</hi> in Scripture is called <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> but this ſeems not to be the Reſurrection here meant; but this Reſurrection is rather to be underſtood of a <hi>bodily</hi> Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and that it <hi>cannot</hi> be meant of <hi>Regeneration,</hi> for theſe Reaſons;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Regeneration</hi> or this <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Reſurrection did begin ſhortly after Man's Fall, and hath continued ever ſince, and ſhall to the End of the World: but the firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection here ſpoken of did not begin ſo early as <hi>Adam's</hi> Fall; but is to <hi>begin</hi> with the <hi>Thouſand Years of Chriſt's Reign;</hi> therefore Regeneration is not the Reſurrection ſpoken of. Again, <hi>(Secondly)</hi> They were the <hi>Souls of Men already beheaded</hi> which <hi>John</hi> ſaw; and their Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection did follow their Death, and not go before it; and twas never known that ever any Man was regenerate after Death: and therefore by Reſurrection here cannot be meant Regeneration. Again, <hi>(Thirdly)</hi> If by Reſurrection here be meant Regeneration; it would follow, that many of the Saints ſhould riſe many Hundred Years before their Reign; there being no leſs Time between their Calling or Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153637:19"/>and the beginning of Chriſt's Kingdom, or the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years of the Saints Reign. Again, <hi>(Fourthly)</hi> If by Reſurrection be meant Regeneration; how can it be that they ſhould reign immediately after their Reſurrection or Regeneration, or begin their Reign all at once, or continue it, but a Thouſand Years.</p>
            <p>Or if any ſhould ſay this Reign is the Saints <hi>reigning with</hi> CHRIST <hi>in Heaven;</hi> ſuch muſt know that tis on <hi>Earth, Rev.</hi> 5.10. And if it were <hi>in Heaven,</hi> it would be more than a Thouſand Years. And beſides, after the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years there will be <hi>an Attempt of War, Rev.</hi> 20. but no Enemy was ever ſo bold as to engage in a <hi>War in Heaven.</hi> And thus we may ſee what lamentable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, if not Abſurdities, will follow upon <hi>ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical</hi> or <hi>Allegorical</hi> Expoſition of Scripture; where a <hi>literal</hi> Interpretation is not contrary to the Analogy of Faith.</p>
            <p>The <hi>next Scripture</hi> we ſhall take Notice of is <hi>John</hi> 5.25.28, <hi>The Hour cometh, and now is, when the Dead ſhall hear the Voice of the Son of God and live, ver.</hi> 25. We are not ignorant that this Scripture, as well as that of <hi>Rev.</hi> 20, is by many, if not moſt, underſtood of ſuch who are <hi>dead in Sin;</hi> who ſhall hear the Voice of Chriſt in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, and ſhall live <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> or be regenerate. But whether this be the Meaning, or (at leaſt) the proper Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtle in this Text, we ſhall Enquire. And here if we view the Context, we ſhall find that Chriſt ſpeaks of <hi>raiſing the Dead</hi> in a <hi>proper</hi> Senſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 21; and of <hi>Judgment to come,</hi> in a <hi>proper</hi> Senſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. &amp; 27. And the Occaſion of this Diſcourſe was, the Cure of the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Man, at which the Jews were offended, and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perſecute Jeſus and ſought to ſlay him, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Chriſt tells them they <hi>ſhould ſee greater Works than theſe, that they might marvell, ver.</hi> 20. he tells them, <hi>that the Hour was coming, and now is, when the Dead ſhould hear his Voice and live:</hi> as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, do ye marvel that I have healed this Man that hath been a Cripple this 38
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153637:19"/>Years; he tells them, that the Hour was Coming when the Dead ſhould hear his Voice and live: and not many Hours after, Chriſt did <hi>raiſe up</hi> dead <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> did ſee it. Nay not long after that, <hi>many dead Bodies of Saints aroſe</hi> by the Power of Chriſt, and appeared to many; and for ought I know, to ſome of <hi>theſe Jews, Mat.</hi> 27.52, 53: So that this was fulfilled according to the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Further, we muſt know that the Word <hi>[Hour]</hi> in Scripture is ſeldom taken for an Hour properly ſo called; but moſtly for a <hi>longer Time;</hi> and ſometimes for Periods of Time, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. mention is made of the <hi>third, ſixth, ninth</hi> and <hi>eleventh Hour:</hi> and ſometimes tis taken for <hi>a very long Time,</hi> even to <hi>Years</hi> and <hi>Ages. The Hour of Temptation which ſhall come upon all the World, Rev.</hi> 3.10, is a <hi>long Hour.</hi> And I have heard, that the ſame Word which is tranſlated <hi>Hour,</hi> in this Text, is in the 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. tranſlated <hi>Time,</hi> viz. <hi>the laſt Time:</hi> and if there be nothing in this <hi>fifth</hi> of <hi>John</hi> repugnant to ſuch a Tranſlation; why ſhould we not as well read it, viz. the <hi>Time</hi> is coming, as well as the <hi>[Hour]</hi> is coming. But upon a Suppoſition, that this former Expoſition be not the Meaning of this 25th Verſe; why then may we not underſtand the Meaning of it to be, the <hi>Time</hi> cometh when the Dead ſhall hear the Voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall live, viz. ſhall riſe and live, and ſo be <hi>the Saints</hi> of the <hi>firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> called <hi>the Reſurrection of the Juſt, Luk.</hi> 14.14; <hi>when God will give Rewards,</hi> which is <hi>at the Sounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, Rev.</hi> 11.15.18. For then there is a Reſurrection, when <hi>the Kingdoms of this World ſhall be the Kingdoms of our Lord, and</hi> when <hi>he ſhall take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf his great Power and reign.</hi> And why may not <hi>theſe</hi> be <hi>the Saints of the firſt Reſurrection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if neither of theſe ſhould be the Saints of the firſt Reſurrection; let us ſee if we can find it in <hi>ver.</hi> 28. Chriſt in this <hi>ver.</hi> tells the <hi>Jews,</hi> they ſhould not marvel at what he had ſpoken before about raiſing the Dead, and the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153637:20"/>of Judgment; but tells them, <hi>the Hour</hi> or Time <hi>was Coming in which ALL that are in Graves ſhould hear his Voice, and come forth, &amp;c.</hi> I think all Men that believe any Thing about a Reſurrection do underſtand, that Chriſt in this <hi>Verſe</hi> ſpeaks of a <hi>Bodily</hi> Reſurrection. But moſt take it for a <hi>ſingle</hi> Reſurrection, viz. of <hi>all</hi> Men Good and Bad <hi>at one Time,</hi> at <hi>the laſt Judgment;</hi> and do utterly deny any firſt or other Reſurrection at all. And I confeſs I ſhould be ready to think ſo too, had not the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. told us in ſo many Words, that there is a <hi>firſt</hi> Reſurrection <hi>ver.</hi> 5, when ſome lived and ſome did not live; and if there be a <hi>firſt</hi> Reſurrection, I am ſure there muſt be a <hi>laſt:</hi> and therefore in <hi>ver.</hi> 13, a <hi>Thouſand Years after the firſt Reſurrection,</hi> we read of <hi>another Reſurrection</hi> to the general Judgment, when <hi>the Sea gave up the Dead that was in it, and Death and Hell gave up the Dead that were in them, and they were judged according to their Works,</hi> at the laſt Judgment. Some there be that think that there is a firſt and laſt Reſurrection comprehended in <hi>this Verſe,</hi> and expound the Words thus; <hi>the Time</hi> is Coming <hi>in which,</hi> i. e. <hi>within the Compaſs whereof,</hi> ALL that are in Graves ſhall hear his Voice, and come forth; they that have done Good to the Reſurrection of Life, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Thouſand Years; and they that have done Evil to the Reſurrection of Damnation, when thoſe Years are ended at the general Judgment: But whether ſo or no I ſhall not determine: But I cannot ſee any Reaſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade me to believe, that Chriſt in the 25th <hi>ver.</hi> of <hi>this Chap.</hi> did intend <hi>Regeneration</hi> or a <hi>ſpiritual Reſurrection;</hi> when the <hi>Sum</hi> of his Diſcourſe was about the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and of <hi>Judgment to come;</hi> and to ſpeak of <hi>Generation</hi> as a Thing <hi>future,</hi> which hath been ever ſince the World began, I do not underſtand: and where they may ſeem to be a double Meaning or doubtful Senſe of any Scripture; It is to be underſtood according to the ſubject <hi>Matter</hi> ſpoken of, and the <hi>Scope</hi> of the Context: Now
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153637:20"/>I am ſure that Chriſt ſpeaks here of a <hi>bodily Reſurrection;</hi> but I am not ſure that he ſpeaks of Regeneration.</p>
            <p>For further Proof of this Point, we ſhall propound one Scripture more to Conſideration; and that is <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15: At the <hi>Sounding of the ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> when <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World ſhall become the Kingdoms of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> there is mention made of <hi>a Judgment, ver.</hi> 18, and of <hi>giving Rewards to his Prophets and Saints;</hi> and this is called there <hi>the Time of the Dead, that they ſhould be judged, ſmall and great.</hi> And this doth neceſſarily imply a Reſurrection, <hi>at leaſt of ſome:</hi> For they are not judged and rewarded before they are raiſed from the dead. But it may be ſome may ſay this is to be underſtood of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection <hi>at the laſt Day;</hi> and that the ſeventh Trumpet here is meant <hi>the laſt Trumpet,</hi> to ſummon the whole World to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the general Judgment. But I ſay no: <hi>That Trumpet</hi> is called <hi>the Trump of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16; ſo is <hi>not this.</hi> Again, <hi>that</hi> is called <hi>the laſt Trump,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15; ſo as after it none was to ſound; ſo is <hi>not this.</hi> Again, at the <hi>Sounding</hi> of the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> of Chriſt's Kingdom in this World, is to <hi>begin,</hi> as hath been proved before; but at the <hi>Sounding</hi> of the <hi>laſt Trumpet,</hi> or Trump of God it ends; for then <hi>the World ends.</hi> So that except we will deny the Doctrine of the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> it muſt be granted, that the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet</hi> is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>laſt Trump:</hi> and ſo that <hi>this</hi> Reſurrection is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>but</hi> the <hi>firſt:</hi> For after <hi>this,</hi> many Things were to be done; and 'tis ſaid <hi>the Nations were angry:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>not</hi> to be underſtood of the <hi>laſt Judgment:</hi> For then 'twill be a vain Thing to be angry.</p>
            <p>Hitherto, or to this Time may be referred that in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2, When <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be ſet as <hi>King in Sion;</hi> there would be much Anger, when he ſhall have the utmoſt Parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſſion; and ſuch of his Enemies as would not that he ſhould reign over them, be bro't forth and ſlain before him, and broken in Pieces with a Rod of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153637:21"/>Iron, like a Potter's Veſſel, and deſtroy them that deſtroy the Earth, and give Rewards to his Servants, ſmall and great. This is called <hi>the Reſurrection of the Juſt, Luk.</hi> 14.14: So that we may gather from hence, that there is a <hi>partial</hi> or <hi>firſt Reſurrection,</hi> and that of <hi>Saints only;</hi> becauſe <hi>they that have Part in the firſt Reſurrection, on them the ſecond Death hath no Power;</hi> but <hi>the reſt of the Dead,</hi> that is <hi>wicked Men,</hi> and <hi>it may be ſome</hi> of the Saints alſo, <hi>ſhall lie ſtill in their Graves</hi> 'till the <hi>general Judgment;</hi> when <hi>all</hi> ſhall appear, Good and Bad, before the Judgment Sent of Chriſt. And 'tis very like this is the Meaning of that Place, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, where 'tis ſaid that <hi>Chriſt ſhall judge both quick and dead, at his appearing, and his Kingdom.</hi> That is to ſay, by judging the <hi>Quick,</hi> that is the <hi>Wicked,</hi> or <hi>ſome of them,</hi> to a <hi>temporal Deſtruction;</hi> and the <hi>raiſed Saints</hi> to <hi>be rewarded</hi> with all the Glory that is promiſed to <hi>all Overcomers</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem, Rev.</hi> 2.7, 11, 17, 27: <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.12, 21: And as an Addition to all the Reſt, <hi>they ſhall ſit with Chriſt in his Throne, even as he overcame and is ſet down with his Father in his Throne:</hi> And theſe are <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Rewards</hi> that are mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18, to be diſtributed to the Saints of the <hi>firſt Reſurrection;</hi> ſo that we may ſay with the <hi>Pſalmiſt; Verily there is a Reward for the Righteous, verily he is a God that judgeth in the Earth, Pſal.</hi> 58. ult.</p>
            <p>By This time I hope it is clear that there is a firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of ſome before all, and that of Saints, and Saints only. And having ſhewed before, what <hi>this firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> is <hi>not,</hi> namely, that 'tis <hi>not Regeneration;</hi> let us now enquire <hi>what it is,</hi> and whether it be not a Reſurrection of the <hi>Body,</hi> and that <hi>properly</hi> ſo called. And to this End, let us conſider, that 20th <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> a little more. <hi>John</hi> is ſaid there to <hi>ſee the the Souls of them that were beheaded for the Witneſs of Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi> What may we think is meant by Souls: <hi>Souls</hi> in this Place are put for <hi>the Dead,</hi> the <hi>Souls of them that were beheaded</hi> is the ſame with the <hi>Dead that were beheaded.</hi> And that is manifeſt from the oppoſite
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153637:21"/>Clauſe or Sentence; i.e. <hi>the reſt of the Dead lived not again, ver. 5;</hi> and therefore the firſt are conſidered as dead.</p>
            <p>Again, 'tis faid <hi>they lived and reigned,</hi> &amp;c. What may be meant by this Living and Reigning? By the Lives of the Souls of them that were beheaded, it ſeems to me to be no other than <hi>the Life of the Body</hi> which they did lay down in the Death of the Body, and which now in the Reſurrection they receive again, <hi>to die no more.</hi> To evince the Truth of this, let it be conſidered;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of the Souls of them that were beheaded, that is of thoſe that were ſlain or dead in Body; and he ſaith that they lived, that is they lived again; but the dead in Body live not again, but by a Reſurrection from the Death of the Body.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Argument</hi> may be thus framed:</p>
            <p>The Reſurrection of the Dead in Body, is the Reſurrec-of the Body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.12, 13.</p>
            <p>but the firſt Reſurrection is the Reſurrection of the Dead in Body; for 'tis the Reſurrection of thoſe that were behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; therefore 'tis of the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Text ſpeaks of ſuch a Reſurrection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Men lived a Thouſand Years after they be raiſed: which cannot agree to any other Life or Reſurrection, but the Life and Reſurrection of the Body; therefore this Reſurrection is a bodily Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Such a Reſurrection is here meant as will be to the reſt of the dead after the Thouſand Years are ended; who lived not again 'till that be finiſhed, <hi>ver.</hi> 5; which ſhall be of the Body, <hi>ver.</hi> 12.13; therefore this Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is of the Body alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Men that were beheaded muſt ſo live during the Thouſand Years, as the reſt of the Dead lived not all that while, their Souls were ſtill ſeparated from their Bodies; therefore theſe muſt live in Souls joined to their Bodies. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Theſe muſt ſo live at the <hi>firſt</hi> Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as the reſt ſhall live at the <hi>ſecond</hi> Reſurrection; and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153637:22"/>that will be in Bodies and Souls united; which cannot be, except they be raiſed from their Graves.</p>
            <p>And thus having written before of the ſecond or next Coming of Chriſt, and of the Thouſand Years, and of the firſt Reſurrection, and the Judgment of the Quick and Dead, and other Things coincident; we ſhall write hereafter a little more fully to what hath been only hinted already in this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> Touching THE KINGDOM OF CHRIST IN THIS WORLD. That of <hi>John</hi> 18.36, being objected againſt it, where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>his Kingdom is not of this World;</hi> for the better Underſtanding of this, we may take Notice, That when <hi>Pilate</hi> aſked Chriſt if <hi>he were a King?</hi> his Anſwer was, <hi>thou ſayſt that I am a King;</hi> grants the Thing, &amp; told him that <hi>for that End he was born,</hi> i. e. <hi>to be a King.</hi> And <hi>Luk.</hi> 19, we read that he was <hi>proclaimed King</hi> by the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: and a great Multitude with great Solemnity, to the Aſtoniſhment of the Spectators: All <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was moved at it: <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.10, and he juſtified them that did it. But it may be ſaid, every one will grant this, that Chriſt is a King, and that he is King over his Church; in which Reſpect he is called <hi>King of Saints, Rev.</hi> 15.3; <hi>King of Sion, Joh.</hi> 12.15, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6; <hi>King Jeſus, Act.</hi> 17.7: But CHRIST is not only <hi>King of Saints,</hi> but <hi>King of Nations, Jer.</hi> 10.7; and that not only as GOD equal with the FATHER, but as MEDIATOR alſo: And in that Reſpect he is called <hi>God's King, Pſal.</hi> 2.6; And <hi>all Power in Heaven and Earth is given to him; Civil</hi> as well as <hi>Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.32.33; there 'tis ſaid, that <hi>God ſhall give to him the Throne of his Father</hi> David, <hi>and that he ſhould reign over the Houſe of</hi> Jacob; and therefore in <hi>Mar.</hi> 11, the People are ſaid to Cry, <hi>Hoſanna, Bleſſed is he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Name of the Lord; bleſſed be the Kingdom of our Father</hi> David. But the Throne and Kingdom of <hi>David</hi> was <hi>Civil Government.</hi> Again, CHRIST is not only a King,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153637:22"/>but <hi>a great King, Mat.</hi> 5,35, in Reference to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is often put for civil State: and not only a great King, but <hi>King of Kings and Lord of Lords, Rev.</hi> 19.16.</p>
            <p>By all which we may ſee, that Chriſt is <hi>de jure,</hi> and will be <hi>de facto,</hi> a King; and that not only over his Church, but <hi>over all the Earth,</hi> and that is next to be conſidered, i. e. THE EXTENT OF CHRIST'S KINGDOM. For this ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. He is <hi>to have the utmoſt Parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Pſal.</hi> 22.28, he is ſaid there to be <hi>Governor among the Nations:</hi> and Pſal. 72.8, <hi>his Dominion is to the Ends of the Earth; ver.</hi> 13. <hi>all Nations ſhall ſerve him. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> alſo ſpeaking of this Kingdom of Chriſt, ſays, <hi>it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a great</hi> Mountain and <hi>filled the whole Earth, Chap.</hi> 2.35: But more fully <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.14; <hi>and there was given to him Dominion and Glory and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him.</hi> I ſhall add one Scripture more to all theſe; and that is <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15, at the <hi>Sound of the 7th Trumpet</hi> tis ſaid, then, that <hi>the Kingdoms of this World are become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt.</hi> By this Time you will underſtand what Chriſt meant <hi>John</hi> 18, when he ſaid, his Kingdom was not of this World; and indeed he himſelf tells us in the following Words, <hi>but</hi> NOW <hi>is my Kingdom not from hence:</hi> as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, I am a King, and ſhall have a Kingdom; but <hi>not now,</hi> not in this World, but in the World to come. For we muſt know that there are more Worlds then one: there was the <hi>old</hi> World which was drowned, and there is <hi>this preſent</hi> evil World: and as the <hi>old</hi> World was drowned, and the Wicked in it were generally, tho' not univerſally deſtroyed by <hi>Water;</hi> ſo will <hi>this preſent</hi> World, and the Wicked that are therein (tho' not all) be deſtroyed by <hi>Fire,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7; as hereafter we ſhall endeavour to ſhew. After which there will be a <hi>new Heaven and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs:</hi> a <hi>new</hi> Face of Things, a <hi>new</hi> World: and this is called by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. <hi>the World to come;</hi> when all Things muſt be put in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153637:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153637:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153637:24"/>to Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And this is the World in which <hi>will be,</hi> or <hi>which is</hi> Chriſt's Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And now to ſpeak a little to this Point; about THE END OF THIS WORLD, and the BEGINNING OF THE WORLD TO COME; and ſee what the Scripture ſpeaks to it. In 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7, the Apoſtle tells us, that <hi>the Heavens &amp; the Earth which are</hi> NOW, <hi>are reſerved unto Fire againſt the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or as ſome render it, <hi>a Day of Judgment, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ungodly Men.</hi> And this <hi>cannot</hi> be meant of the <hi>ultimate Judgment;</hi> becauſe after this, there will not only be a <hi>new Heaven,</hi> but a <hi>new Earth</hi> alſo, <hi>wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, <hi>righteous Men;</hi> and that <hi>they ſhall build Houſes, and plant Vineyards, and eat the Fruit of them, Iſai.</hi> 65.21; yea and worſhip God with external Worſhip, <hi>from one Sabbath to another;</hi> and that not for a little While, but theſe new Heavens and new Earth are <hi>to remain,</hi> Chap. 66.22. But what then may we think will become of the <hi>old</hi> Heaven and the old Earth? Will they not ſtill have a Being? For <hi>anſwer</hi> hereunto, we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the Apoſtle in the forementioned <hi>Chap,</hi> doth make a Parallel between the Deſtruction of the <hi>old</hi> world and the World <hi>that now is;</hi> that as the <hi>old</hi> World was deſtroyed by <hi>Water,</hi> ſo will <hi>this</hi> World be by <hi>Fire,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, as to that which is to be deſtroyed. For as in the <hi>old</hi> World there was not an Annihilation of any Thing, nor were all Men nor all the Brute-Creatures Deſtroyed, nor were the empyrean or ſtarry Heavens then touched; and therefore tis only the aerial <hi>Heavens,</hi> with what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them, which are the Furniture of them, or what moves in the Air, that will be the Subject of this <hi>Burning;</hi> and it may be that which the Apoſtle means by <hi>Elements melting with fervent Heat,</hi> which diſtinguiſheth from the <hi>Heavens;</hi> for it cannot be that the <hi>Elements properly ſo called,</hi> ſhould melt with fervent Heat; the <hi>Water</hi> not being capable of burning or melting; the <hi>Fire</hi> is that which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153637:24"/>burns all Things, and therefore not to be burned: and for the <hi>Earth,</hi> as it was not deſtroyed by the <hi>Flood,</hi> tho' much defaced; ſo neither will it be deſtroyed by <hi>Fire,</hi> ſo as not to be: but <hi>this Fire</hi> ſhall rather be for the <hi>Reſtoration</hi> of it, than the Deſtruction of it: <hi>as a Veſture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed, Pſal.</hi> 102.6. But that the Earth ſhall have a habitable Being after the End of the Thouſand Years, is clear from <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.8; <hi>the Devil ſhall go forth to deceive the Nations that are in the four Quarters of the Earth;</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 9, <hi>they went</hi> accordingly <hi>upon the Breadth of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>but it may be ſome may think, that <hi>this Burning</hi> of the World will be <hi>at</hi> or <hi>after</hi> the <hi>general Judgment:</hi> but for ought I know it may be otherwiſe: for <hi>then the Heaven and the Earth</hi> is ſaid to <hi>fly away from the Face of him that ſat on the Throne</hi> to judge the World: and it hath been before ſhewed, that after this Burning, there will be a <hi>new Earth</hi> as well as <hi>a new Heaven.</hi> And who can tell, but that this may be the Time when that ſhall be fulfilled, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.19, 20, when <hi>there ſhall be Blood and Fire and Vapours of Smoak; ſo as the Sun ſhall be darkened</hi> with it, and <hi>the Moon appear as Blood:</hi> [as we have lately ſeen in this Country, Vapours of Smoak have cauſed them ſo to appear:] for that was to be <hi>in the laſt Days;</hi> and we do not know that ever this hath been accompliſhed: and that this is not at the general Judgment but before, is clear out of <hi>Joel</hi> 2.32: For at this very Time when this ſhall come to paſs, and the World ſhall be burned, ſome ſhall be delivered; <hi>for in Mount Sion and in Jeruſalem ſhall be Deliverance, and the Lord hath ſaid it, ver.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>The Sum is, that at the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> there will be a great Deſtruction of the Wicked of the World, as hath been before ſhewed; and this will be by <hi>Fire,</hi> as the Wicked of the <hi>old</hi> World were deſtroyed by <hi>Water:</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>this Fire</hi> is <hi>for the Perdition of ungodly Men. Paul</hi> alſo tells us that Chriſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153637:25"/>will be <hi>revealed from Heaven in flaming Fire to take Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on wicked Men,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8. But more clear <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.15; <hi>For behold the Lord will come with Fire, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Anger with Fury, and his Rebukes with Flames of Fire; for by Fire and by Sword will the Lord plead with all Fleſh, and the Slain of the Lord ſhall be many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what then may we think will become of <hi>good Men,</hi> and the <hi>irrational Creatures,</hi> at this Time, when the world ſhall be in a Flame? how ſhall they be ſaved? Indeed this is a Queſtion too hard for me, or any Man elſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; neither do I know that it is revealed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: yet for Reſolution of this, I propound to Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>(Firſt,)</hi> That when the World was deſtroyed by <hi>Water,</hi> tis poſſible <hi>ſome good Men</hi> might periſh in that Deſtruction; who ſeeing that Deluge coming on the World might repent, and ſo have their Souls ſaved: and if ſo, why may not ſome good Men be taken away in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Deſtruction by <hi>Fire,</hi> as to their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and be raiſed to Heaven, as <hi>Elias</hi> was, in fiery Chariots, and their <hi>Souls</hi> be ſaved. But <hi>(Secondly)</hi> tho' we do not know how they ſhall be ſaved; yet <hi>the Lord knows how to deliver the godly out of Temptation, when the Unjuſt ſhall be reſerved to the Day of Judgment to be puniſhed,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9: and we know, that <hi>Faith hath quenched the Violence of Fire, Heb.</hi> 11.34; and that the Fire that burnt up the moſt mighty Men that were in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Army, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.20, had no Power over the Bodies of his Saints: and there are <hi>ſome who ſhall dwell with devouring Fire and everlaſting Burnings;</hi> when <hi>ſome ſhall not,</hi> but ſhall be <hi>as the burning of Lime, and as Thornes cut up, ſhall they be burnt in the Fire, Iſai.</hi> 33.12, 14, 15: And there is a Promiſe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.2, that God made to his People, that <hi>when they walk through the Fire they ſhould not be burnt, neither ſhould the Flames kindle upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, when God deſtroyed the <hi>old</hi> World by <hi>Water,</hi> God found out a Way to preſerve <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Family,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153637:25"/>and Creatures of every Kind; when as neither <hi>Noah,</hi> nor all the World beſides, could tell <hi>how</hi> it would be, till God revealed it. Nor can any Thing that I know be certainly concluded, <hi>how</hi> he will preſerve his Church at this Time: but that he will have a glorious Church on Earth, when there ſhall be <hi>a new Heaven</hi> and <hi>a new Earth,</hi> is a Thing which we muſt and ought to believe, which will be after all this.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>irrational Creatures,</hi> as Birds and Beaſts of all Kinds; we may upon good Grounds ſuppoſe, that ſome of every Kind will be preſerved, as they were when the World was drowned; though the greateſt Part may be deſtroyed as they were then. That theſe Creatures ſhall have a Being after this Time we may gather from Scripture; becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8, <hi>they wait, groan, and travel in Pain.</hi> But what do they wait and groan for? is it to be annihilated, and have no Being? we may not think ſo; for every Creature by natural inſtinct, labours to propagate their own Kind, and to preſerve their own Beings: and therefore tis ſaid <hi>ver.</hi> 19, that <hi>they with earneſt Expectation, wait for the Manifeſtation of the Sons of God:</hi> which whether it be at, or during the Time of the general Judgment, (as ſome would have it) or any Time before, (as others underſtand;) it proves clearly they ſhall have a Being after this Deſtruction made by Fire. Again, <hi>they wait for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from the Bondage of Corruption into the glorious Liberty of the Children of God, ver.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>And here we muſt underſtand, that God in the Beginning made all Things in their firſt Beings very good; free from that Vanity they are now ſubject to; and it was <hi>ſubjected to Vanity</hi> after the Fall, <hi>not willingly, yet in hope of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</hi> This Vanity and Bondage of Corruption is the Curſe upon the Creature for Man's Sin; and this is that, it waits to be delivered from; and to be ſerviceable to thoſe Ends for which they were firſt made; i. e. next to the Glory of God, for the Uſe and Service of Man.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153637:26"/>
            <p>And here, it may not be amiſs to enquire, whether <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men</hi> may not make Uſe of the Creature without abuſing them to Sin?</p>
            <p>There is no doubt to me, but wicked Men, and that by God's Appointment, have a right to the Creature; and may, for any Thing I know, make uſe of them without Offence. It was <hi>God</hi> that <hi>divided to the Nations their Inheritance, Deut.</hi> 32.8: <hi>he gave Mount Seir to Eſau for a Poſſeſſion;</hi> and <hi>to the Moabites and Amonites their</hi> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; and <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not to meddle with them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.5.9. But more fully, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3, God delivered into the Hands of <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>his Poſterity,</hi> ſome of whom were none of the beſt, the Beaſts of the Earth, Fowls of the Air, Fiſhes of the Sea, and every moving Thing that lives, and the green Herb to be meat for them: and as long as they made uſe of them for no other End, who can ſay the Creature was abuſed? We may rather think they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, if they uſe them not, for thoſe Ends for which they were appointed even by God himſelf: And therefore do not yet ſee any Reaſon to believe, that this is any Part of that Vanity and Bondage the Creature waits and groans to be delivered from. I am not ignorant, that ſome are of another Opinion; who think that the Creatures ſhall never be delivered from this Vanity and Bondage; but ſtill be ſubject to it ſo long as any Wicked Men are in the World and make uſe of them: and therefore conceive, that the Time when the Creature ſhall be delivered from the Curſe of Vanity &amp; Bondage it now groans under, is not before the general Judgment, but in and during the continuance of it.</p>
            <p>But for further clearing of this, let us conſider; <hi>(Firſt)</hi> What's meant by <hi>Adoption,</hi> and what by <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of our <hi>Body;</hi> which the Creature, as well as Believers, wait for, and groan for. <hi>Adoption</hi> I take in Scripture Senſe to be the making one a Son, who was not ſo before: and this is done to every Believer at his firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: ſo that Believers cannot be ſaid to wait for <hi>this,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153637:26"/>which they have already received: and therefore <hi>Adoption</hi> cannot be taken in this Senſe here: for they that are ſaid to wait for the Adoption, <hi>had the Spirit of Adoption before, whereby they cried Abba: ver.</hi> 15: and therefore by <hi>Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 23, I underſtand, nothing but <hi>the Manifeſtation of that Adoption</hi> they were before Partakers of: and this is that the Creature waiteth for <hi>ver.</hi> 19, <hi>the Manifeſtation of the Sons of God.</hi> And this agrees directly with 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1.2, <hi>beloved,</hi> NOW <hi>we are the Sons of God; but it doth not yet appear,</hi> viz. to the World; but it <hi>ſhall appear:</hi> But when ſhall it appear? It ſhall appear, <hi>when Chriſt ſhall appear;</hi> which we have proved before will be long before the general Judgment. <hi>This Adoption</hi> is called <hi>the Redemption of our Body:</hi> and the Apoſtle ſeems to make it all one with <hi>Adoption;</hi> but whether it be ſo, or no, I ſhall not determine, but leave it to the Judgment of the Learned: and proceed to examine, what may be meant by <hi>Redemption</hi> in <hi>this Place.</hi> And here we muſt underſtand that there are ſeveral Acceptations of the Word <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in Scripture, and it may various Ways be underſtood; but I ſhall mention only <hi>two. Firſt,</hi> a Redemption of our <hi>Souls</hi> by the Blood of Chriſt from Curſe and Wrath and all our ſpiritual Enemies: and this is done at our <hi>firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, Eph.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24, 25. Again, there is a <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal</hi> Redemption; or a Redemption of our <hi>Bodies,</hi> from outward Enemies, when <hi>God will redeem his Church out of all their Troubles, Pſal.</hi> 25.22: and <hi>this</hi> is that <hi>which hath been ſpoken of by all the holy Prophets ſince the World began; that we ſhould be ſaved from our Enemies and from the Hands of all that hate us; that we might ſerve him without Fear, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the Days of our Lives,</hi> Luk. 1.70: and this in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23, is called <hi>the Redemption of our</hi> BODY, not <hi>Bodies;</hi> but <hi>the Body myſtical,</hi> the <hi>Body of which Chriſt is the Head,</hi> which is his Church. To this Purpoſe is that in <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.27.28; <hi>when the Son of Man cometh in the Clouds of Heaven with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153637:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153637:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153637:28"/>Power and great Glory; then look up and lift up your Heads, for your</hi> REDEMPTION <hi>draweth nigh.</hi> And this was the Burden of that new Song ſung, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5, 9. that <hi>Chriſt had redeemed them by his Blood,</hi> and that <hi>they ſhould reign on Earth.</hi> And in this Senſe I underſtand that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3. 4; where <hi>the Hundred and forty four Thouſand ſtanding on Mount Sion with the Lamb,</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>redeemed from the Earth,</hi> and <hi>redeemed from amongſt Men; ſinging a new Song which none elſe could learn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See alſo how the Creatures are brought in rejoicing at this Time, when the Lord reigneth; as if it were the only Thing they waited and groaned for, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96; <hi>The Heavens rejoicing, the Earth glad, Fields joyful, and all that is therein;</hi> which comprehend all Land-Creatures; <hi>all the Trees of the Wood; Sion heard and was glad, and the Daughters of Judah rejoiced.</hi> But what is the Ground of all this Joy and Rejoicing? Why, 'tis becauſe of God's Judgments on a wicked World, in burning up his and our Enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.3; delivering his Church, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. Methinks this looks very well like <hi>the Time</hi> that <hi>the whole Creation groaneth and travaileth in Pain,</hi> for the Fruition and Enjoyment of.</p>
            <p>But it may be thought, that all this Joy and Rejoicing will be during the Time of the <hi>general Judgment.</hi> And it may as well be thought otherwiſe, and that it will be <hi>long before</hi> that Time: For at this Time <hi>the Earth ſhall be eſtabliſhed, that it ſhall not be moved;</hi> and when <hi>they ſhould bring Offerings to God, and come into his Courts, and worſhip him in the Beauty of Holineſs,</hi> with external Worſhip; which will not be at the ultimate Judgment.</p>
            <p>To all that which hath been already written touching this Matter, may be added; that there ſhall be a Time when the <hi>Enmity of the Creature ſhall ceaſe,</hi> both their Enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Man, and one againſt another: For there was no ſuch Enmity in them before the Fall; and 'tis no ſmall Part of the Curſe brought on the Creature, and that Vanity
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153637:28"/>they were made ſubject to, and they groan &amp; travail in Pain to be delivered from; being ſubjected to it in Hope of Deliverance: and it ſhall be delivered from this Bondage of Corruption, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>See ſome Scriptures to this Purpoſe. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.16, 17, 18, <hi>in the Day</hi> when <hi>the Church ſhould call Chriſt Iſhi, and the Name of Baalim ſhould be taken out of her Mouth; in that Day God would make a Covenant for them with the Beaſts of the Field, and with the Fowls of the Heaven, and with the creeping Things of the Ground; and break the Bow, the Sword, and the Battle, out of the Earth; and they ſhould lie down ſafely.</hi> Moreover, God promiſeth that <hi>in that Day he would hear the Heavens, and the Heavens ſhould hear the Earth, and the Earth hear the Corn, and Wine, and Oyl, and they ſhould hear Jezreel.</hi> See here is <hi>Safety, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Plenty:</hi> and this will be before the End of the World.</p>
            <p>But more full is that, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.6, 7, 8, 9, <hi>the Wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard lie down with the Kid, and the Calf and the young Lion, and a little Child ſhould lead them; and the Cow and the Bear ſhould feed their young ones, and lie down together.</hi> Here we ſee the Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Creatures one againſt another ſhall ceaſe; and not only ſo, but their Enmity againſt <hi>Man</hi> alſo: So that <hi>the ſucking Child ſhall play on the Hole of the Aſp, and the wean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Child put his Hand on the Cockatrice Den; they ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all God's holy Mountain; for the Earth ſhall be filled with the Knowledge of the Lord as the Waters cover the Sea.</hi> The whole <hi>Chapter</hi> is nothing elſe but a Deſcription of the Kingdom of Chriſt in <hi>this World;</hi> as is intimated to us in the Contents of the Chapter; and will be fulfilled at or about <hi>the Calling of the Jews:</hi> for it will be in that Day, as is clear <hi>ver.</hi> 11; and it cannot, without Wrong to the Scriptures, be referred to the general Judgment. You have the ſame and much more, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65. from <hi>ver.</hi> 17, to the <hi>End:</hi> and this will be when there ſhall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153637:29"/>be <hi>a new Heaven</hi> and <hi>a new Earth;</hi> and none in their right Underſtanding can refer it to any other Time. And here we are told that by <hi>Wolfe,</hi> and <hi>Lyon,</hi> and <hi>Leopard,</hi> are meant <hi>Men</hi> of a ravenous Diſpoſition before Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which afterward become <hi>Lambs:</hi> but if ſo, then they are no longer Lyons and Leopards, but Lambs; and tis no Wonder if they feed and lie down together. Or if any ſhould think that by theſe ravenous Creatures are meant <hi>wicked Men</hi> under the Power of reſtraining Grace: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though tis true, there will be wicked Men at this Time in the World, and poſſibly may be much under Reſtraint; yet tis to be doubted, whether they ſhall have ſuch Intimacy of Communion with the Saints, as to Eat, and Drink, and lie down together in God's holy Mountain; or that they will be ſo tame, that a little Child ſhould lead them. For we know, there will ſtill be Enmity between the Seed of the Woman and the Seed of the Serpent; when the Enmity of the Creature ſhall ceaſe. But what need is there of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the <hi>literal</hi> Interpretation of theſe Scriptures, unleſs Truth were endangered thereby; or to make <hi>Allegories</hi> or <hi>Metaphors</hi> where God makes none? Thoſe that know any Thing in theſe Matters, know or may know, that this Enmity of the Creatures amongſt themſelves, and againſt Man (which is a great Part of the Curſe) ſhall be taken away and ceaſe; and they wait in Hope for it, as hath been before ſhewed: and if ſo, why not now? Why muſt it be deferred till the <hi>general Judgment</hi> is begun, or during that Time? Tis doubtful whether <hi>theſe irrational Creatures</hi> will have a Being at the <hi>General Judgment:</hi> or if they ſhould have a Being, to be ſure they could not be of any Uſe unto Men, which was one great End of their Beings. I know no Reaſon for ſuch an Opinion, but this, that wicked Men will abuſe them. Such have been told before, that Uſe either for Meat or any other Uſe or Employment is not in itſelf ſinful, but lawful and good: and we may not think, that wicked Men will be ſo apt to abuſe them (if at all)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153637:29"/>when the Devil is in Chains, and they themſelves under the ſtrict Government of the Saints. And as a further Anſwer to ſuch, if theſe <hi>irrational Creatures</hi> ſhould have a Being during the Time of the general Judgment (which is yet to be proved;) what Children will there be then at Leiſure to lead them? or have nothing elſe to do, but to play about their Holes? when ſmall as well as great, and Children as well as others, muſt ſtand before Jeſus Chriſt to be judged, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12; and the Earth &amp; the Heavens will then fly away from the Face of him that ſits on the Throne, and no Place found for them, <hi>ver.</hi> 11: and if ſo, then no Place for theſe Creatures to be, or not to be ſuſtained in any ordinary Way. Methinks Men of Underſtanding ſhould be aſhamed of theſe Opinions, which will neceſſarily draw ſo many Abſurdities with them, as theſe and ſuch others as might be mentioned.</p>
            <p>In the next Place, ſomething may be written about THE NEW JERUSALEM mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 21; and enquire what the Scripture ſpeaks to this Point. And herein I ſhall rather modeſtly propoſe, than poſitively conclude, in a Matter of ſuch Difficulty; concerning which there are ſuch various Apprehenſions. And here <hi>(Firſt)</hi> We muſt know that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in Scripture is divers Ways taken. And firſt it is taken for a <hi>City</hi> ſo called in <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> which ſome think was built by <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 14; afterward called <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> but whether ſo or no, I ſhall not determine: but ſure we are, it was in <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Time, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.1; but never conquered by him, tho' he ſlew <hi>Adonibezeck</hi> who was King thereof; but 'twas inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> 'till <hi>David</hi>'s Time, and then taken by him, and became the Royal City, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards burned by the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> re-edified by <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> and at laſt deſtroyed by the <hi>Romans;</hi> built again by <hi>Aelianus Adrianus,</hi> but <hi>not in the ſame Place:</hi> but <hi>it ſhall be inhabited again in her own Place, even in Jeruſalem,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153637:30"/>Zech.</hi> 12.6. &amp; 14.10; <hi>when there ſhall be a new Heaven and a new Earth, Jeruſalem ſhall be a Rejoicing, and her People a Joy:</hi> but I do <hi>not</hi> underſtand this to be <hi>the new Jeruſalem,</hi> of which we are now ſpeaking. Again, by <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is underſtood <hi>the Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5, <hi>Jeruſalem went out and were baptized of John in Jordan;</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſaid to <hi>kill the Prophets,</hi> viz. the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Furthermore, by <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is meant <hi>all the People of the Land, as they were a civil State and common Wealth:</hi> and this is very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the Scriptures of the old Teſtament; <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.8, <hi>Be thou inſtructed O Jeruſalem, leſt I make thee a Land not inhabited.</hi> So <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.2, God bids the Prophet <hi>cry in the Ears of Jeruſalem;</hi> that is, cry that ſo that whole People might hear, and underſtand: for tho' <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is only named, as being the Head City; yet the Expoſtulation is with <hi>the whole Land,</hi> as may appear in the Sequell of that Chapter. See <hi>Iſai.</hi> 24.23, tis ſaid there that <hi>Chriſt ſhall reign in Mount Sion,</hi> that is his Church, <hi>and in Jeruſalem,</hi> that is <hi>the civil State,</hi> for ſo I underſtand it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.12, <hi>Praiſe the Lord O Jeruſalem, praiſe thy God O Sion;</hi> i. e. both Church and State. Again, tho' the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> is ordinarily repreſented to us under the Name and Notion of <hi>Sion;</hi> yet ſometimes alſo under the Name of <hi>Jeruſalem, Pſal.</hi> 137.6, <hi>If I prefer not Jeruſalem above my chief Joy:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6, <hi>Pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem; and give him no Reſt till he make Jeruſalem a Praiſe in the Earth.</hi> In further Proſecution of the Thing in Hand, we ſhall take into Conſideration, what is mentioned in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26, to our Purpoſe: where the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>two Covenants,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>a two-fold Diſpenſation of the ſame Covenant;</hi> the one <hi>legal,</hi> as given by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>ceremonial</hi> Law, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till the Coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh; the other <hi>evangelical,</hi> as given by CHRIST and <hi>his Apoſtles;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> I underſtand to be <hi>Jeruſalem which is above,</hi> and is no other than the <hi>Goſpel Church</hi> conſiſting both of <hi>Jews</hi> and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153637:30"/>and tis ſaid to be <hi>above,</hi> becauſe tis more ſpiritual and glorious: for tho' tis true, the legal Diſpenſation of the Covenant was glorious, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7; yet that Glory was to be done away, and was no Glory in Compariſon, by Reaſon of the Glory that excelleth: For if that which is done away was glorious, much more that which remaineth is glorious. The Church of old had many glorious Titles or Epithets, as have been ſhewed before; called <hi>his Glory, Iſai.</hi> 46.13; <hi>his Treaſure, his pleaſant Portion,</hi> &amp;c: yet ſpeaking of the Goſpel Church, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.3, ſtiles it <hi>the Houſe of his Glory, a Crown of Glory, a royal Diadem.</hi> Such and ſo high are the Titles given to the Goſpel Church; that many if not moſt that think any Thing of the <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi> conceive <hi>this</hi> to be <hi>the new Jeruſalem,</hi> at leaſt in the Inchoation of it: but tis poſſible ſuch may be miſtaken: for the Glory of the <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi> doth as far tranſcend and excel <hi>this Goſpel-Church,</hi> as <hi>this</hi> doth <hi>that</hi> under the <hi>legal Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and much more, and that in many Reſpects, as it may be we may hereafter ſhew.</p>
            <p>There are others who think, and that not a few, that <hi>this new Jeruſalem</hi> is <hi>Heaven</hi> itſelf: the Deſcription of it being ſo glorious, think tis impoſſible it ſhould be <hi>in this World:</hi> and he was once counted a Fool who thought it would be in this World: but that tis not Heaven itſelf, we ſhall hereafter endeavour to ſhew. Some others ſuppoſe it ſhall be in this World; and that tis no other then the <hi>Jewiſh Church after their Converſion to Chriſt</hi> or Chriſtianity: and whoſoever reads the whole 60th <hi>Chapter</hi> will be ready to think, that <hi>this</hi> is <hi>new Jeruſalem.</hi> Indeed, and I muſt needs ſay, it looks very well like it; and there are many Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in it agreeing with the Deſcription of the <hi>new Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Rev.</hi> 21; and therefore I ſhall be ſlow to think or ſay they are miſtaken; [tho' I am not of their Opinion.] For the Scripture ſpeaks very much of the Glory of this Church and People, as hath been ſhewed before, <hi>when it ſhall turn to the Lord, and the Vail that is upon their Heart ſhall be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153637:31"/>taken away,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16; and <hi>the receiving them again</hi> into God's Covenant <hi>be as Life from the Dead:</hi> and therefore ſome have thought that <hi>this</hi> is <hi>the Bride, the Lamb's Wife.</hi> What Priviledges they ſhall have in the Kingdom of Chriſt above the <hi>Gentile Churches</hi> I cannot tell: but the Prophet <hi>Micah, Chap.</hi> 4.8, tells us, that <hi>they were the Tower of the Flock,</hi> and that <hi>the firſt Dominion ſhould come to the Daughter of Jeruſalem:</hi> and yet <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> are <hi>all one</hi> in CHRIST JESUS, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</p>
            <p>But tho' theſe bid very fair for it, yet neither theſe, nor any other who have been mentioned, (in my Underſtanding) are the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> of which we ſpeal. But in further Proſecution of the Thing under Conſideration, we ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>(Firſt)</hi> what it is, and <hi>(Secondly)</hi> whence it comes. To the <hi>Firſt, what it is:</hi> And here according to Scripture I underſtand it to be, <hi>a diſtinct Society of Saints, and of Saints only,</hi> whoſe Names are written in the Book of Life, <hi>coming down from God out of Heaven;</hi> wholly free from Sin. Sorrow, and Suffering; who have attained to Perfection in Grace and Holineſs, ſo as they need no further Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of external Means of Salvation. <hi>Firſt</hi> they are a <hi>Society:</hi> therefore called <hi>a City; the great City, Rev.</hi> 21.10; <hi>the holy City, ver.</hi> 2; <hi>the beloved City, Chap.</hi> 20.9; <hi>the City of God, Rev.</hi> 3.12; [of Saints and Saints only]: and yer <hi>not</hi> comprehending <hi>all Saints;</hi> becauſe there are <hi>Nations of them that are ſaved who ſhall walk in the Light of it, Chap.</hi> 21.24; and <hi>they ſhall bring the Glory and Honour of the Nations into it, ver.</hi> 26. Beſides, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.9; there is mention made of <hi>the Camp of the Saints, and the beloved City;</hi> which ſeems to imply (at leaſt to me) that they are <hi>diſtinct Societies.</hi> No ſuch a Society in the pureſt Churches and in the beſt Times; Tares will be amongſt Wheat till Harveſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.29. <hi>[Coming down from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.]</hi> Tis true, the Goſpel Church is called <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> but <hi>not coming down from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> therefore is not Heaven itſelf; for it comes down
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153637:31"/>from God out of Heaven, <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.2.10. Again, <hi>the Kings of the Earth do bring their Glory and Honour to it,</hi> and <hi>they ſhall bring the Glory and Honour of the Nations into it;</hi> which they cannot bring into Heaven. Again, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9, tis ſaid, that <hi>God and Magog went upon the Breadth of the Earth, and compaſſed the Camp of the Saints and the beloved City:</hi> therefore they were <hi>upon the Earth:</hi> for if by <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> be meant <hi>Heaven,</hi> is a Thing altogether impoſſible. Furthermore, the Saints of the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> are free from Sin, Sorrow, and Suffering: (1) from <hi>Sin;</hi> there is <hi>nothing in it that defileth, Chap.</hi> 21.27; but Sin defileth: (2) They are free from <hi>Sorrow, ver.</hi> 4; <hi>no more Sorrow, nor Crying, nor Pain:</hi> and alſo free from <hi>Suffering;</hi> for Suffering is always attended with Pain: But in other Saints there will be Sin, and therefore Sorrow and Suffering, to the End of the World. Again, theſe have attained to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Grace and Holineſs, ſo as they need no further Improvement of external Means of Salvation: <hi>no Temple therein, no Need of Sun and Moon,</hi> to ſhine therein; <hi>for the Glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof, ver.</hi> 22.23; <hi>no Night there, nor Need of Candle, or Sun; for the Lord giveth them Light, Chap.</hi> 22.5. But we know that external Means of Salvation will be needful for ſome till the End of the World; by which Souls may be brought home to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus having given what my Apprehenſions are in this Matter, and ſhewed <hi>what</hi> this <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> is <hi>not,</hi> and alſo <hi>what it is</hi> and <hi>whence it comes;</hi> let it be enquired into, <hi>where</hi> ſuch a Society of Saints and Saints only, according to the former Deſcription, may be found. And here, as I premiſed at firſt, I will not be poſitive, but propoſe to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, <hi>whether they may not be the Saints of the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> mention'd <hi>Rev.</hi> 20? That ſome Saints ſhall riſe before others, is clear in that <hi>Chapter,</hi> in the beginning of the Thouſand Years, as before: whether <hi>all Saints</hi> or no, I ſhall not determine: that <hi>ſome</hi> ſhall not then live when <hi>theſe</hi> are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153637:32"/>raiſed, is as clear; whether Saints, or Sinners, or both, is left to Conſideration. That there will be <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> in the World, during that whole Term of Time, and ſo until the End thereof, and to the End of the World, we have good Ground from Scripture to believe: that Chriſt will appear long before the End of the World or ultimate Day, hath been formerly proved: that when he cometh, he will come with all his Saints, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5; <hi>Jude</hi> 14: and why not theſe Saints that come with Chriſt be the <hi>new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem coming down from God out of Heaven, who are to live and reign with Chriſt a Thouſand Years, Chap.</hi> 20; and that <hi>on Earth, Chap.</hi> 5.10? Again, why may not theſe be <hi>the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect,</hi> and <hi>Church of the firſt born to which we are come, Heb.</hi> 12.23, or what elſe is the Meaning of that Place? Once more, why may not theſe be <hi>thoſe who ſtand on Mount Sion with the Lamb, Rev.</hi> 14, and <hi>follow him whitherſoever he goes, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from among Men, being the firſt Fruits unto God and to the Lamb;</hi> who were <hi>without Fault before the Throne of God?</hi> and are <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the <hi>four Beaſts</hi> and <hi>the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> which I underſtand to be the Church which will be at that Time. If theſe or ſome of theſe be not the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> I know not where to find it.</p>
            <p>I know that very few are of this Opinion, that the <hi>raiſed Saints</hi> are the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> but rather think that the <hi>New Heaven and New Earth,</hi> of which <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>2d Epiſtle, 3d Chap.</hi> 13. are the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi> for Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in this Caſe, and as an Addition to what hath been already written; I ſhall propoſe to Conſideration, (1.) Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinking ſo, or ſaying ſo, without any Proof, will make it ſo? (2dly.) the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> makes them <hi>two diſtinct Things, Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2. The <hi>New Heaven and New Earth,</hi> ſeems to be quite another Thing; and I underſtand it to be no other than the <hi>Jewiſh evangelical Church,</hi> repreſented to us after a legal Manner by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> under the Name &amp; Notion of a <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Temple;</hi> which is like to be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153637:32"/>the moſt glorious Church that ever was in the World; 'tis more than poſſible, that <hi>this</hi> may be the <hi>New Heaven and New Earth,</hi> when <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall be a Rejoicing, and her People a Joy, Iſa.</hi> 65.17, 18; being called there the <hi>New Heaven, and New the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding <hi>this New Heaven and New Earth,</hi> as it is diſcribed by <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> differs in many Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> as will appear by compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>John</hi> &amp; <hi>Ezek.</hi> together. For, firſt, In the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> there is <hi>no Temple; for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb are the Temple thereof, Rev.</hi> 21.22; but that City mentioned by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> had a <hi>Temple, Chap.</hi> 41.1, 4; implying that there ſhould be external Worſhip: And what elſe is the Meaning of the <hi>Prieſts and Offerings</hi> ſo often mentioned there? See <hi>Zec.</hi> 14.16. Again, in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> the <hi>River of the Waters of Life,</hi> proceedeth out of the <hi>Throne</hi> of God and the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1; but in that Houſe mentioned by <hi>Ezekiel, Chap.</hi> 47.1; the <hi>Waters</hi> (not the River of the Waters of Life) iſſueth from <hi>under the Threſhold</hi> of the Houſe, at the South Side of the Altar. <hi>(Thirdly)</hi> In the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> is <hi>the Tree of Life</hi> on either Side of the River, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. but by that River that ſhall iſſue out of the Sanctuary of that City in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſhall grow <hi>Trees for Meat, Chap.</hi> 47.12. Again, once more, and once for all, this City <hi>new Jeruſalem comes down from God out of Heaven,</hi> and whither doth it come but to the <hi>new Heaven and new Earth?</hi> for the <hi>firſt Heaven and Earth were paſſed away, Rev.</hi> 21.1, 2; <hi>they ſhall not be remembered, nor come into Mind, Iſai.</hi> 65.17. All theſe Things being conſidered, it ſeems to me impoſſible that this <hi>new Heaven and new Earth</hi> ſhould be the <hi>ſame</hi> with the <hi>new Jeruſalem.</hi> The Sum is this; <hi>Peter</hi> tells us of a <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and new Earth,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> of a <hi>City and Temple;</hi> but neither of them tells us that either of theſe is the <hi>new Jeruſalem:</hi> It remains then that <hi>John</hi> and <hi>John only</hi> (for ought I know) ſpeaks of <hi>this new Jeruſalem:</hi> And for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153637:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153637:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:153637:34"/>ought I yet ſee, that which hath been already propoſed in, and touching this Matter, is moſt likely to be the <hi>new Jeruſalem.</hi> It may be thought, that enough, if not too much, hath been written about this Matter, and leſs might have been better: but if it be not true, it is too much; and if it be true, tis too little. I having obſerved how much Men differ in their Apprehenſions about it, have conſidered the more of it: and however ſome Men may think it but a ſmall Matter, yet they may be miſtaken: if they are the true Sayings of God, bleſſed are they that read and hear them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.3: and <hi>this new Jeruſalem</hi> is no other then <hi>the Bride, the Lambs Wife;</hi> as is clear from <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, compar'd with <hi>ver.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome with ſay, tis impoſſible, for Souls coming down from Heaven after their Bodies have been raiſed from the Dead, and Bodies and Souls united together, to live on Earth and converſe amongſt Men who are in a State of Mortality. But that may be poſſible, which to us may ſeem impoſſible; for with God all Things are poſſible, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.26. And we know <hi>CHRIST</hi> did ſo, after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection forty Days together: and doubtleſs <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> both in Souls and Bodies appeared to ſome of the Apoſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.3, and they took great Delight and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment therein. And why then may not the raiſed Saints be ſo repreſented, as to have and hold a holy and heavenly Correſpondence with Men on Earth; appearing and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at Pleaſure, even as Chriſt did before he aſcended. Again, why not <hi>raiſed Saints</hi> as well as <hi>Angels?</hi> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared both to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lott, Gen.</hi> 18.2; &amp; 19.1; as Men with human Bodies, eating of ſuch Things as were ſet before them: yea CHRIST himſelf <hi>after his Reſurrection,</hi> is ſaid to <hi>eat a Piece of a broiled Fiſh, and of an Honey Comb, Luk.</hi> 24.42.</p>
            <p>Thus having written already ſomething of the next or ſecond Coming of Chriſt, of the firſt Reſurrection, of the new Jeruſalem, and ſeveral Things to come; I ſhall in the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153637:34"/>next Place write ſomething of GOG &amp; MAGOG; who, by the Inſtigation of the Devil, ſhall be <hi>gathered together at the End of the</hi> 1000 <hi>Years</hi> to engage in a War againſt the Camp of the Saints and the beloved City, mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. And here we ſhall enquire <hi>firſt,</hi> who this <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> may be; and whether this <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> mentioned by <hi>John,</hi> be the ſame of whom <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Chap.</hi> 38, and 39.</p>
            <p>The Scripture indeed ſpeaks of <hi>Magog,</hi> who was one of the Sons of <hi>Japhet, Gen.</hi> 10.2; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 1.5: but I do not remember it ſpeaks of <hi>Gog</hi> until the Time of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel, Chap.</hi> 38.3; where he is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned as <hi>the chief Prince of Meſhech and Tuball:</hi> Neither do I remember that ever I read or heard of any one Nation that ever were called by that Name: and therefore I think they are a <hi>Compound</hi> of <hi>many Nations,</hi> repreſented to us by that Name, both by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> as will appear by comparing <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 38.5, 6, with <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.8; they were ſuch as the Prophets of old had ſpoken of, <hi>ver.</hi> 17, by <hi>ſome other Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>next</hi> Thing to be enquired into is, whether this <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> mentioned by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> be the ſame which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Rev</hi> 20. For clearing of this, we may conſider, <hi>(firſt)</hi> the <hi>Time,</hi> when theſe Enemies of God and of his Church ſhall appear in Arms; and (2dly) with or <hi>againſt whom</hi> they ſhall engage; and (3dly) the <hi>Occaſion</hi> or moving Cauſe thereof. <hi>(Firſt)</hi> for the <hi>Time:</hi> and here we muſt underſtand, that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſpoken of by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> are to be Contemporaries with the <hi>Jews</hi> either at the Time or not long after their Return to their own Land; as appears by the whole Story, <hi>Chap.</hi> 38. &amp; 39, to which the Reader is referred. (2dly) The Perſons <hi>againſt whom</hi> they are to engage in this War: and they are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> tho' it may be not only with them. (3dly) the <hi>Occaſion</hi> or moving Cauſe: and that ſeems to be, either the Weakneſs of that Nation at this Time, as not being yet ſettled in their own Land, or their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153637:35"/>Security, or both, as <hi>ver.</hi> 11; but it was chiefly to ſpoil them, or to make a Prey of them, as <hi>ver.</hi> 12. And now let us conſider, whether theſe Characters will agree with that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſpoken of before <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>(Firſt)</hi> as to the <hi>Time</hi> of this War; <hi>the one</hi> being at or not long after the Return of the <hi>Jews</hi> to their own Land, <hi>Preparation</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto will be under the pouring out of the <hi>6th Vial;</hi> and <hi>the other</hi> will not be till the <hi>End of the Thouſand Years,</hi> and <hi>after the looſing of Satan out of the bottomleſs Pit.</hi> (2dly) <hi>One</hi> will engage principally againſt the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but <hi>the other</hi> will be againſt the <hi>whole Church</hi> of God, conſiſting both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> repreſented to us under the Name and Notion of <hi>the Camp of the Saints, and the beloved City.</hi> (3dly) As to the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of this War, viz. the Weakneſs of this People, or their Security, or, both, or to take or make a Spoil of them, in <hi>the one;</hi> but no ſuch Thing is hinted, nor can be ſuppoſed concerning the other. But that which will put all out of doubt, that this <hi>Gog</hi> &amp; <hi>Magog</hi> mentioned by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is <hi>not</hi> the ſame ſpoken of by <hi>John,</hi> is this; in <hi>the one,</hi> we have a Propheſy of a Battle, <hi>a great Battle,</hi> and ſuch as was never heard of before in the World; but in <hi>the other, no Battle at all,</hi> no Stroak ſtruck on either Side: for when once this great Battle is over, <hi>they ſhall learn War no more, Swords muſt be turned to Plow Shears, and Spears to pruning Hooks; when God ſhall judge the Nations and rebuke many People, Iſai.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>In further Proſecution of the Matter propoſed to be ſpoken to, we ſhall find, that the Scripture makes mention of <hi>three great Battles</hi> which are yet future; or it may be, one Battel foretold in three ſeveral Places of Scripture, viz. by <hi>two Prophets</hi> and <hi>one Apoſtle,</hi> viz. by <hi>Joel, Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>John:</hi> and it is called by <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 16.14, <hi>the Battle of the great Day of God Almighty.</hi> Somewhat of this Battel hath been ſpoken of before Page 17, to which the Reader is referred. I ſhall ſpeak a little more of it here. You have been told there of <hi>the Kings of the Earth and of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153637:35"/>whole World being gathered together:</hi> we tell you now, <hi>tis</hi> GOD <hi>that gathereth them together: Joel</hi> 3.2, <hi>I will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Nations and bring them down to the Valley of Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat:</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 38.16, ſpeaking concerning <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> God ſaith, <hi>I will bring thee againſt my Land;</hi> and ſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.16, <hi>He gathered them into a Place called Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageddon;</hi> for ſo I am told the Word may be rendered. Again, they all three declare, that this Warlike Aſſembly will be <hi>principally</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews, Chap.</hi> 38.8, 16; <hi>Joel</hi> 3.1; <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12; and that it will be in the Land of <hi>Judea</hi> that they ſhall be deſtroyed: And they all ſhew, the dreadful Effects that will follow, <hi>Chap.</hi> 38.19, 20; <hi>Joel</hi> 3.15.16; <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18, 19, 20. And all agree that when this Battle is over, there will be <hi>a peaceable and proſperous State of the Church;</hi> this being the laſt Battle that ever will be fought in the World. So that if we view theſe Scriptures, we ſhall ſee that they all ſpeak of the ſame Enemies, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together by the ſame Hand, engaged againſt the ſame People, at the ſame Time, upon the ſame Occaſion, to be deſtroyed in the ſame Place; and the ſame Effects to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, viz. terrible to the one, and comfortable to the other. So that you ſee this War is not a War, in which, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God ſhall fight one againſt another, as they often do upon divers Occaſions; but it will be a Combination of them all againſt CHRIST and <hi>his People,</hi> and <hi>ſpecially his antient People.</hi> And <hi>theſe</hi> are as I underſtand the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> intended by <hi>Ezekiel;</hi> and the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 20, are <hi>the multiplied Poſterity of thoſe few of the Nations that ſhall be left when this Battle is over, at the beginning of the Thouſand Years;</hi> when the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> foretold by <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed in <hi>Armageddon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, tis very likely there will be great Wars, and much Blood ſhed, and the <hi>Jews</hi> after their Return to their own Land will be much diminiſhed &amp; brought very low, as we may read in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153637:36"/>
               <hi>There ſhall be ſuch a Time of Trouble as never was ſince there was a Nation even to that ſame Time,</hi> and <hi>at that Time ſhall thy People be delivered:</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> tells us, that <hi>many of them ſhall be cut off and die, Chap.</hi> 13.8; <hi>the City taken and Houſes rifled, and Women raviſhed, before the Lord go forth and fight againſt theſe Nations, in the Battle of the great Day of God Almighty.</hi> For tis a great doubt to me, whether all this while that Nation will be converted to Chriſt and embrace Chriſtianity, until they be in their own Land, and this great Battle be over. For tis very unlikely, conſidering how theſe dry Bones lie ſcattered moſt Parts of the World over, and do hardly know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of what Nation they are, much leſs do others know, and it may be ſpeak divers Languages, and how the Goſpel ſhould be preached to them and to their Underſtandings, and by whom and in what Tongue, and whether ſeeing they have had the Goſpel preached at leaſt to their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors already, who did reject it, and as they ſtill do; what Probability is there, that they will now readily embrace it, and that ſo ſuddenly, ſo as to be born in a Day; who hath heard ſuch a Thing? who hath ſeen ſuch Things? ſhall the Earth bring forth in one Day? or ſhall a Nation be born (or new born) at once? for as ſoon as Sion travelled ſhe brought forth her Children, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.8. I rather incline to think, that God will ſome Way or other, firſt bring them into their own Land, and give them Advantage to return by <hi>drying up the River</hi> EUPHRATES, that is as I conceive by diminiſhing and abating the great Power of the <hi>Turk</hi> in and about that Part of the World; and that either by inteſtine Commotions, or Wars with other Nations, or both; that ſo a Way may be prepared for <hi>theſe Kings of the Eaſt</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn: and this is to be done under the <hi>pouring out</hi> of the <hi>6th Vial:</hi> and now is the Time when <hi>theſe dry Bones will come together and ſtand upon their Feet, and become an exceeding great Army, and have Breath breathed into them,</hi> and have a <hi>Civil Life</hi> put into them, but <hi>no ſpiritual Life</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:153637:36"/>till they be in their own Land, and at the <hi>Sound</hi> of the <hi>7th Trumpet</hi> and the <hi>pouring out of the 7th Vial:</hi> and <hi>after this great Battle,</hi> when God will deſtroy all Nations that come againſt <hi>Jeruſalem, then he will pour upon them the Spirit of Grace &amp; Supplication;</hi> and then, will CHRIST <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally</hi> &amp; viſibly <hi>appear, and they ſhall look on him whom they have pierced and mourn,</hi> with a penetential Mourning: and when <hi>his Feet ſhall ſtand on the Mount of Olives,</hi> from whence he aſcended, <hi>then he will come and all his Saints with him, Zech.</hi> 14.3.5. And <hi>this is the great Day of</hi> JEZREEL, <hi>when the Children of Judah and the Children of Iſrael ſhall be gathered together and appoint them one Head, Hoſ.</hi> 1. <hi>ult; when the Lord ſhall be King over all the Earth, Zech.</hi> 14.9; and <hi>all the Kingdoms of this World become his, Rev.</hi> 11.15: and <hi>now will Michael ſtand up, the great Prince, which ſtandeth for the Children of</hi> Daniel's <hi>People;</hi> and then <hi>they ſhall b e delivered:</hi> and <hi>all this</hi> a <hi>Thouſand Years before the general Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sum of all, and that which I intend is this, viz. That, the <hi>Gog</hi> &amp; <hi>Magog</hi> ſpoken of by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is not the ſame ſpoken of by <hi>John</hi> Rev. 20; nor any one Nation, but a Compound of many Nations, who ſhall engage in a War, not one with another, but <hi>principally</hi> with the <hi>Jews;</hi> and that after their Return to their own Land, Way being made for them, by the Weakening of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power on the Borders of <hi>Euphrates;</hi> and after many Conflicts the <hi>Jews</hi> will be brought very low and much diminiſhed; and many Nations ſhall be gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Battle againſt them to deſtroy them; this Battle ſpoken of by <hi>Ezekiel, Joel</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> yet no ſpiritual Life till the Sound of the <hi>7th Trumpet</hi> and the pouring out of the <hi>7th Vial,</hi> which probably will be by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; when they ſhall be converted to Chriſtianity, partly by Viſion, Chriſt perſonally appearing to them, whom they ſhall look upon and ſee with their Bodily Eyes and mourn, under a deep Senſe of their Sin; and then tis likely will cry out as thoſe converted <hi>Jews. Act.</hi> 2.37, <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:153637:37"/>and as <hi>Paul</hi> when ſtruck down, <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> then poſſibly the Goſpel may be preached to them, as it was to thoſe, and three Times three Thouſand converted at one Sermon, and that fulfil'd the Prophet ſpoken of before, that <hi>a Nation it born at once,</hi> and their Feet be accounted beautiful that bring theſe glad Tidings to them; and then, and never till then, will they ſay, <hi>bleſſed is he that cometh to us in the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (God aſſiſting) I ſhall write a little about the POURING OUT OF THE SPIRIT UPON ALL FLESH, which is yet future, at leaſt in Part, and as to the full Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and as a Concommitant of all theſe Things, from <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29; <hi>It ſhall come to paſs afterwards that I will pour out my Spirit upon all Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And here ſeveral Things offer themſelves to Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as <hi>firſt</hi> what's meant by <hi>Spirit;</hi> and what by <hi>pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out;</hi> as alſo who are the <hi>Subjects of it;</hi> together with the <hi>Effects</hi> thereof; and then laſtly, as to the <hi>Time</hi> when this ſhall be, intimated in the Word <hi>afterwards:</hi> ſomething may be written briefly to theſe Things.</p>
            <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> what's meant by POURING OUT OF THE SPIRIT. And here we muſt know, that the Communication of THE SPIRIT is repreſented to us in Scripture more Ways than one, as ſometimes by <hi>Donation,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.13, God is ſaid there to <hi>give us his Spirit: John</hi> 14.16, God the Father is ſaid there to <hi>give the Comforter,</hi> which is <hi>his Spirit: Luk.</hi> 11.13, <hi>how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give his Spirit to them that aſk it?</hi> Again, ſometimes tis repreſented to us by <hi>Miſſion,</hi> or ſending: <hi>John</hi> 14.26, Chriſt tells them, that <hi>the Father would ſend the holy Ghoſt that ſhould teach them all Things:</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.7, he tells them again, he <hi>would ſend the Comforter: Gal.</hi> 4.6, God is ſaid there to <hi>ſend forth the Spirit of his Son into our Hearts.</hi> Sometimes alſo, by <hi>Aſperſion,</hi> or ſprinkling: hence Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>ſprinkle many Nations, Iſai.</hi> 52.15: and to <hi>ſprinkle
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153637:37"/>clean Water upon them, Ezekiel</hi> 36.25; which I underſtand of <hi>the Spirit.</hi> Again, ſometimes by <hi>Infuſion</hi> or putting his Spirit in us, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 36.27; and <hi>Chap.</hi> 37.14. And the laſt that I ſhall mention is, by <hi>Effuſion</hi> or pouring out of his Spirit upon us; as in the Text propoſed to be ſpoken to, quoted alſo by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 2.17: we have the ſame Expreſſion of <hi>pouring of the Spirit, Iſai.</hi> 44.3; as alſo <hi>Chap.</hi> 32.15, where <hi>the Spirit</hi> is promiſed to be <hi>poured out from on High:</hi> we have the like Expreſſion, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10: there is one Scripture more, and all that at preſent is with me, where this Expreſſion of pouring out the Spirit is uſed, and that is <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23, <hi>behold I will pour out my Spirit upon you,</hi> &amp;c. But what may we think is meant by <hi>pouring out? Pouring out</hi> in Scripture doth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, if not always ſignify, an Abundance of that which is poured forth: as when God brings <hi>Abundance of Wrath</hi> on a People, he is ſaid to <hi>pour out his Wrath,</hi> as we might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily inſtance in Scripture: hence we read of ſo many <hi>Vials of Wrath</hi> which were to be <hi>poured out</hi> on them that were the Subjects of them until they were deſtroyed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16: the like is ſaid when God promiſeth <hi>Abundance of Mercy,</hi> he is ſaid to <hi>pour it out,</hi> as in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10: God ſaith there that he would <hi>open the Windows of Heaven and pour out ſuch a Bleſſing as there ſhould not be Room to receive it.</hi> So that we ſee what is meant by <hi>pouring forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Thing to be inquired into is what is meant by <hi>Spirit</hi> which is thus to be poured out? By <hi>Spirit</hi> in this Place, I do <hi>not</hi> underſtand the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the HOLY SPIRIT: tho' that is ſaid to <hi>dwell</hi> in all Believers, and <hi>if any Man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his, Rom.</hi> 8.9; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.14: Neither do I think, by <hi>Spirit</hi> here is meant the <hi>ordinary Gifts</hi> of the Spirit, which every Believer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives at his firſt Converſion. But I think by <hi>Spirit</hi> in this Place is meant a <hi>plentiful Effuſion</hi> of the <hi>Gifts</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which are <hi>extraordinary:</hi> as will evidently appear if we compare this Text with <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17; and take the poſtle
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153637:38"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi>'s Commentary on the Words. For it cannot be denied, but that the Apoſtles, and for any Thing that I know, others that were with them at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> after Chriſt was aſcended, they all had received the <hi>ordinary</hi> Gifts of the Spirit at their firſt Converſion; and yet they were to wait there for <hi>the Promiſe</hi> of the Father, which Chriſt hath told them of before, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.49: But what was this Promiſe? only of more and higher Degrees of the <hi>ordinary</hi> Gifts of the Spirit which they had already received? I cannot think ſo; and the Conſequence doth make it evidently to appear that it was otherwiſe. But <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where</hi> was <hi>this Promiſe</hi> of the Father made which they were to wait for? The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> when they began to ſpeak with other Tongues, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.4; in the 16th Verſe tells them, that <hi>this was that which was ſpoken of by the Prophet Joel;</hi> and therefore this in my Underſtanding is the Promiſe of the Father which they were to wait for; conſiſting only in the pouring out of <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts both of Tongues, Propheſy and Miracles.</p>
            <p>The next Thing to be conſidered, is the <hi>Subjects</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepients upon whom the Spirit was thus to be poured out: and that the <hi>Prophet</hi> tells us, and after him the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that tis upon <hi>all Fleſh.</hi> By <hi>all Fleſh,</hi> here we are <hi>not</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>all Mankind,</hi> as tis taken in <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.12, where tis ſaid that <hi>all Fleſh had corrupted their Way.</hi> No, nor are we to underſtand it of <hi>all Saints</hi> neither; but <hi>ſome of all Sorts and Sexes,</hi> viz. Jews and Gentiles, young and old, Male and Female, Sons and Daughters, Servants and Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids. And there were <hi>above an Hundred beſides the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and that Women as well as Men, aſſembled together at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> waiting for this Promiſe: <hi>Act.</hi> 1.14.15, <hi>and they were all with one accord in one Place; Chap.</hi> 2.1, <hi>and they were all filled with the holy Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak with other Tongues as the Spirit gave them Utterance;</hi> and that not only upon <hi>Jews,</hi> but upon <hi>Gentiles,</hi> alſo were poured out the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt, as we may ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 10.45, 46. Upon <hi>Cornelius,</hi> his Family, and his Kindred, and near
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153637:38"/>Friends, ver. 24: and in Chap. 19. ver. 2, we read of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> that were <hi>Believers</hi> and doubtleſs had received the <hi>ordinary</hi> Gifts of the Spirit, and ſuch as were ſaving; and yet were <hi>Strangers</hi> to theſe <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts, till <hi>Paul</hi> laid his Hands on them, and then they received theſe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> Gifts, and <hi>ſpake with Tongues and did Propheſy:</hi> and tis very likely theſe were Gentiles. The firſt Effect then that followed after the pouring out of the Spirit was the <hi>Gift of Tongues;</hi> the Goſpel being now to be preached to all the World, and the Diſciples being moſt of them, if not all, unlearned Men; the Wiſdom of God ſaw it neceſſary in order thereunto, to give them to ſpeak and to underſtand all Languages, that thoſe Nations to whom they were to preach might underſtand what was ſpoken. Tis true indeed, this Gift of Tongues, nor Miracles, is not mentioned by <hi>Joel:</hi> but yet <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, and we muſt believe him, that when they thus ſpake with Tongues, <hi>this was that which was ſpoken of</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Joel;</hi> without which they could not Propheſy, or preach the Goſpel to all Nations, or to the Edification of them to whom they were to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>The next Thing therefore we ſhall take Notice of is that which is mentioned both by the <hi>Prophet</hi> and the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> and that is <hi>Propheſy.</hi> Propheſy in Scripture is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken for a foretelling of Things to come: much of what the Prophets ſpake in Times paſt was then future when ſpoken: the <hi>whole</hi> Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> is called a <hi>Propheſy, Chap.</hi> 1.3; and yet when made known to <hi>John</hi> was all future, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. But I do not underſtand Propheſy in this Senſe in this Place, (tho' I do not know but God may ſometimes in an extraordinary Way, make known to ſome of his Servants Things to come) for there were <hi>Prophets</hi> in the primative Times, as we may read <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1; as <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> and <hi>Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Lucius,</hi> and <hi>Manaen,</hi> and <hi>Saul;</hi> and theſe were called their <hi>Teachers.</hi> We read alſo <hi>Act.</hi> 11.27, of <hi>Prophets</hi> which <hi>came from Jeruſalem to Antioch,</hi> of whom <hi>Agabus</hi> was one, <hi>who ſignified by the Spirit that there ſhould
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153637:39"/>be a great Dearth in all the World, which came to paſs in the Days of Claudius Caeſar:</hi> and in <hi>Act.</hi> 15.32, we read of <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> that were <hi>Prophets:</hi> and <hi>Act.</hi> 19.7, tis ſaid there were <hi>twelve Diſciples at Epheſus which did propheſy:</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was more than a Prophet, ſpeaks very much of <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Propheſying,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. &amp; 14; and ſaith expreſly, that God <hi>hath ſet in his Church next after Apoſtles,</hi> PROPHETS: and we read not only of <hi>Prophets,</hi> but <hi>Propheteſſes</hi> alſo, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.8.9. <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Deacon</hi> had <hi>four Daughters</hi> that were Virgins that did <hi>Propheſy.</hi> I do not think, that all good Men and Women could Propheſy: the Apoſtle ſeems to deny that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12; <hi>Are all Prophets? are all Teachers? do all work Miracles? or do all ſpeak with Tongues? but there are Diverſity of Gifts, but the ſame</hi> Spirit; as the Apoſtle ſhews at large 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. And indeed it was for <hi>this very End,</hi> amongſt others, that <hi>Chriſt aſcended to give Gifts to Men;</hi> and that not only <hi>ordinary,</hi> but <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and the Gift of <hi>Propheſy</hi> as well as others, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11: and Chriſt told his Diſciples, that <hi>if he did not aſcend, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter would not</hi> come: but had they not the <hi>ſaving</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Power of the Spirit already, and the <hi>ordinary Gifts</hi> of the Spirit long before this Time? yea doubtleſs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs be meant not of higher Degrees &amp; greater Meaſures of the <hi>ordinary</hi> Gifts of the Spirit only, but of thoſe which was <hi>extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Effect of pouring out the Spirit was, <hi>ſeeing of Viſions</hi> and <hi>dreaming of Dreams;</hi> of which I ſhall write a little, and but a little. We know that God revealed his Mind to his Servants, and ſometimes to others alſo in the old Teſtament, often by <hi>Viſions,</hi> and by <hi>Dreams. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had a <hi>Viſion, Gen.</hi> 15.1; and tis like a <hi>Dream</hi> alſo <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Jacob</hi> had a <hi>Dream, Chap.</hi> 31.11: <hi>Joſeph</hi> had <hi>two Dreams: Moſes</hi> had a <hi>Viſion, Exod.</hi> 3.2: <hi>Job</hi> had his <hi>Dreams</hi> and <hi>Viſions,</hi> tho' they were a Terror to him, <hi>Job.</hi> 7.14: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had <hi>Viſions, Chap.</hi> 1.1; &amp; 6.1: <hi>Ezekiel</hi> had
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153637:39"/>many, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.1. And we read in the New Teſtament, <hi>Joſeph</hi> had a <hi>Dream</hi> to fly into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and a <hi>Dream</hi> to return out of <hi>Egypt, Mat.</hi> 2.13.19: <hi>the wiſe Men</hi> were warned by a <hi>Dream,</hi> not to return to <hi>Jeruſalem, ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Zecharias</hi> had a <hi>Viſion, Luk.</hi> 1.22. And after the ſending of the Spirit by extraordinary Gifts, <hi>Annanias</hi> had a <hi>Viſion Act.</hi> 9.10: <hi>Cornelius</hi> had a <hi>Viſion, Act.</hi> 10.3: <hi>Peter</hi> alſo ſaw a <hi>Viſion, ver.</hi> 17: <hi>Paul</hi> had a <hi>Viſion, Act.</hi> 16.9; yea more then one, for he had as many as he could well bear, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.1: much of <hi>the Revelation</hi> was made known to <hi>John</hi> by <hi>Viſion.</hi> And tis likely, the Effects of pouring out the Spirit are not all recorded in Scripture: yet we muſt and ought to believe, that either they have been or ſhall be fulfilled: but it hath been ſhewed that it hath been poured out in an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Way upon <hi>Jews</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentiles,</hi> young and old, Male and Female, Servants &amp; Handmaids. Now of <hi>other Effects,</hi> about the Sun being turned into Darkneſs and the Moon into Blood, we have written ſomething of this before; and therefore ſhall forbear to write of it here; and come to</p>
            <p>The <hi>laſt Thing</hi> propoſed to be ſpoken to; and that is the TIME to which this Propheſy doth refer, held forth in the Word <hi>Afterward.</hi> This Word <hi>Afterward,</hi> ſeems to refer to ſome remarkable Time which was to go before it; and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> renders it in other Words, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17, <hi>It ſhall come to paſs in the laſt Days:</hi> but both the <hi>Prophet</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle</hi> agree in this, that tis a moſt remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Period of Time, a Fore-runner of <hi>the great &amp; terrible Day of the Lord,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks; and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> after him calls it <hi>the notable Day of the Lord.</hi> And indeed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we take it as paſt, or future, it hath been both <hi>notable</hi> and <hi>terrible,</hi> and will yet be more <hi>notable</hi> and <hi>terrible,</hi> when this Propheſy ſhall be fully accompliſhed: <hi>Notable</hi> to the People of God that call on him; for they ſhall be ſaved, <hi>ver.</hi> 21: but <hi>terrible</hi> to his and their Enemies; for they ſhall be deſtroyed: <hi>Multitudes, Multitudes in the Valley
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153637:40"/>of Deciſion, for the Day of the Lord is near in the Valley of Deciſion, Joel</hi> 3.14. The right Underſtanding of <hi>the Time</hi> to which this Prophecy refers, will give great Light to the Point under Conſideration. 'Tis true indeed, this Prophecy was in Part fulfilled immediately after Chriſt's Aſcention: but that there is yet a further Accompliſhment of it to be expected, will eaſily be made to appear: for ſome prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Scriptures may be fulfilled more than once: but to ſpeak a little more fully to <hi>the Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are <hi>two remarkable Periods of Time</hi> recorded in Scripture, beſides the ultimate Period: the <hi>one</hi> is already <hi>paſt,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> is yet <hi>to come:</hi> the <hi>one</hi> at &amp; <hi>ſoon after</hi> the <hi>firſt Coming</hi> of CHRIST; and this Time was much ſpoken of in the Scriptures; and this the Apoſtle calls <hi>the Fulneſs of Time, Gal.</hi> 4.4: and this was a moſt remarkable Time, when the Son of God became the Son of Man to ſave poor loſt Men: <hi>This</hi> was <hi>a great Day,</hi> and <hi>many great Things</hi> were done at <hi>this Time:</hi> The Way of inſtituted Worſhip wholly chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the ceremonial Law aboliſhed, and another Way appointed by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt inſtead thereof; the Levitical Prieſthood laid aſide or changed, and Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters appointed to ſupply that Place; the national Church ceaſed; the <hi>Jews</hi> rejecting the Goſpel, are caſt off; and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> receiving the Goſpel, are taken into their Room; City and Temple ruined; the Nation, Multitudes, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes deſtroyed, the reſt ſcattered all the World over; the Goſpel to be preached to all Nations; to that End, <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Gifts</hi> are given, and many other Things done which might be mentioned: And therefore <hi>this</hi> was <hi>a great Day,</hi> both <hi>notable</hi> &amp; <hi>terrible:</hi> And this <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>the laſt Days;</hi> it <hi>ſhall come in the laſt Days: Paul</hi> alſo calls Goſpel Times, <hi>the laſt Days; Heb.</hi> 1.1, <hi>in theſe laſt Days God hath ſpoken to us by his Son.</hi> There is alſo <hi>the latter Part</hi> of <hi>the laſt Days;</hi> and this is alſo called <hi>the laſt Days, Iſa.</hi> 2.2. The Prophet there tells us, that <hi>in the laſt Days the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the Top of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153637:40"/>Mountains, &amp; be exalted above the Hills:</hi> And leſt any ſhould think this hath been already fulfilled, the 4th Verſe will tell us <hi>no;</hi> for it will be when <hi>Swords muſt be beaten into Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares, and Spears into Pruning-Hooks,</hi> and when <hi>they ſhould learn War no more:</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that <hi>in the laſt Days ſhall come perilous Times;</hi> that is <hi>the latter Part</hi> of <hi>the laſt Days,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1: This is called alſo <hi>the latter Times,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, when <hi>ſome ſhall depart from the Faith. Job</hi> tells us, that CHRIST <hi>ſhall ſtand at the latter Day upon the Earth, Chap.</hi> 19.25. <hi>Baalim</hi> alſo propheſied what great Things God would do for <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>the latter Days.</hi> I will advertiſe thee <hi>what this People ſhall do to thy People in the latter Days, Numb.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Hoſea</hi> alſo ſpeaking of the <hi>Calling</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſaith it will be <hi>in the latter Days; Chap.</hi> 3.5, <hi>they ſhall fear the Lord and his Goodneſs in the latter Days.</hi> So that we ſee there is <hi>the laſt Days,</hi> and <hi>the latter Part</hi> of <hi>the laſt Days;</hi> and yet all this <hi>long before</hi> the <hi>ultimate Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is yet <hi>another remarkable Period of Time</hi> which is yet <hi>future;</hi> and that will be at the <hi>ſecond</hi> or <hi>next Coming of</hi> CHRIST. His <hi>firſt Coming</hi> was to put away Sin by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of himſelf; his <hi>ſecond Coming</hi> will be without Sin to our Salvation, of which we have written before: his <hi>firſt Coming</hi> was mean in outward Appearance; his <hi>ſecond Coming</hi> will be unſpeakably glorious, <hi>with Power and great Glory, Matt.</hi> 24. <hi>When he comes to build up</hi> Sion, <hi>he will appear in his Glory, Pſa.</hi> 102.16: Then <hi>he will come with Ten Thouſand of his Saints,</hi> and <hi>take unto himſelf his great Power and reign,</hi> and <hi>all the Kingdoms of this World become his, Rev.</hi> 11.15; deal wonderfully with and for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.26.</p>
            <p>I do not know any one Thing in Scripture more inſiſted on, than <hi>the Glory</hi> of <hi>the latter Part</hi> of <hi>the laſt Days,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> of the Kingdom of Chriſt, until the laſt Judgment. A ſhort Account of ſeveral Things which will then be done, have already been given in this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153637:41"/>Diſcourſe: but 'tis beyond my Underſtanding to declare <hi>what great Things are yet to be done in the World;</hi> and how much of Prophecy is yet unfulfilled. And among other Things, there will be a more full Accompliſhment of the <hi>pouring out of the Spirit</hi> in <hi>converting Grace,</hi> and the <hi>ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gifts and Graces of the</hi> SPIRIT, both upon <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> when <hi>the Spirit ſhall be poured out from on High, Iſa.</hi> 32.15; and <hi>the Wilderneſs</hi> (that is as I underſtand the <hi>Jews</hi> be called) <hi>becomes a fruitful Field, and the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Field becomes a Foreſt;</hi> that is <hi>the Fulueſs</hi> of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> be <hi>brought in.</hi> There is a <hi>double Fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; one</hi> is from the Time of the <hi>Jews</hi> Rejection, until their Converſion: This is called, <hi>the Riches of the World,</hi> and <hi>the Riches of the Gentiles, Rev.</hi> 11.12: And this is alſo called, <hi>the Fulneſs of the Gentiles, ver.</hi> 25. There is alſo <hi>another Fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and that is to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence ſoon after</hi> or <hi>in Conjunction with</hi> the <hi>Calling</hi> of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and this is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12, compared with <hi>ver.</hi> 15. From the <hi>Fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> there will be a <hi>greater Fulneſs</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> than ever they had before: It will be <hi>Life from the Dead, ver.</hi> 15: for the <hi>Gentiles</hi> at this Time, in all Likelihood, will be in a low Condition, till <hi>the Glory of the Lord be riſen</hi> upon the <hi>Jews; Darkneſs will cover the Earth, and groſs Darkneſs the People, Iſai.</hi> 60.2: and that not only to the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Gentile Nations,</hi> but <hi>wiſe</hi> as well as <hi>fooliſh Virgins</hi> will be <hi>ſlumbering and ſleeping; little Faith on Earth, when the Son of Man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> little Hope of reviving the Work of Converſion, till this Time be over. We have a ſad Deſcription of the <hi>latter Part of the laſt Times,</hi> immediately preceeding this remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Time before ſpoken of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. And tis very likely, that thoſe <hi>Gentile Nations,</hi> that do not now come in, will never come in, nor be converted: <hi>Upon them ſhall be no Rain, that come not to Jeruſalem to worſhip the King, the Lord of Hoſts, and to keep the Feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> Zech. 14.17, 19: And this will be a remarkable Time and a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153637:41"/>great Day, when <hi>the Children of Judah, and the Children of Iſrael ſhall be gathered together, and appoint them one Head;</hi> it will then be <hi>the great 'Day of Jezreel, Hoſ.</hi> 3.5: Yet I do <hi>not</hi> underſtand this Day to be <hi>the great and terrible 'Day of the Lord,</hi> of which <hi>Joel</hi> ſpeaks; for that is to be AFTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARD; that is, after the <hi>Jews</hi> are <hi>called,</hi> and <hi>the Fulneſs of the Gentiles are come in</hi> to the Obedience of the Goſpel. Neither do I conceive, that yet either <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> had received any other Gifts of the Spirit than thoſe that were <hi>ordinary:</hi> neither were <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts ever given to any (that I know of) but to thoſe who were already <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,</hi> nor given together with ſaving Grace, and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Gifts of the Spirit: Neither do I think, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth intend at all any other Gifts but ſuch as are <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> in this Propheſy: for if when the Goſpel was firſt to be preached to all Nations, God ſaw that <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Gifts were neceſſary; and therefore tho' the Apoſtles had commiſſion to go teach all Nations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19; yet they muſt <hi>tarry at Jeruſalem,</hi> till they were furniſhed with <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts: and why are not <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts neceſſary as well <hi>now,</hi> as they were <hi>then,</hi> the Caſe being the ſame? Tis true, by Virtue of their former Commiſſion, they did preach to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but were forbidden to go into the Way of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> till now: And as Chriſt gave <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Grifts</hi> for the Publication of the Goſpel to all Nations, ſo he appointed <hi>extraordinary Officers</hi> for that Work; <hi>ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, Eph.</hi> 4.11; and gave them ſuitable Power for the Execution of their reſpective Commiſſions: And we have good Reaſon to believe, that when the Goſpel was preached to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the End being attained, that theſe <hi>extraordinary Gifts</hi> of Tongues, Propheſy, and Miracles, ceaſed; as the Apoſtle foretold they ſhould, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8; and conſequently there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, all <hi>extraordinary Officers,</hi> and what Power they had been veſted withal. And for ought I know, this may be a good Anſwer to thoſe that are of Opinion, that there is Church
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153637:42"/>Power reſident in <hi>ſome other</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Perſons beſides ordinary ſtated Church Officers: but if there be ſuch an Order of Men in the Worl, pray what may we call <hi>their Names?</hi> have they Scripture Names? are they Apoſtles, or Prophets, or Evangeliſts? or can they work Miracles? or have they the Gifts of Healing? CHRIST always gives <hi>Names</hi> to <hi>all his Officers,</hi> and ſtates the <hi>Duties</hi> of their Places; and if they are <hi>extraordinary Officers,</hi> they muſt have an <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Call:</hi> but <hi>haec obiter:</hi> [i.e. <hi>ly the Way</hi>]</p>
            <p>And now having written briefly what may be meant by <hi>Spirit</hi> in this Propheſy, and what by <hi>pouring out</hi> upon all Fleſh, together with the <hi>Effects</hi> of it, and ſomething as to the <hi>Time,</hi> viz. the laſt Days as <hi>Peter</hi> renders it; all which hath been Accompliſhed <hi>in Part</hi> or <hi>in whole:</hi> That there is yet a <hi>further</hi> and <hi>future</hi> fulfilling of it, is more than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable: and that will appear, if we view the <hi>Context</hi> both <hi>before</hi> and <hi>after.</hi> It will be in thoſe Days and at that T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me when <hi>God will bring again the Captivity of Judah and Jeruſalem, be jealous for his Land and pity his People,</hi> do great Thing for them, deal wonderfully with them, <hi>ver.</hi> 26, <hi>when Judah ſhall dwell forever and Jeruſalem from Generation to Generation;</hi> and after he hath <hi>poured out upon them the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, Zec.</hi> 12.10; and they be converted to Chriſtianity. When theſe Things ſhall be fulfilled, all which is yet to come, then <hi>afterward</hi> the <hi>Spirit ſhall he poured out on all Fleſh;</hi> then, and not till then: and all this will be before <hi>the great and terrible Day of the Lord</hi> come. For further Demonſtration hereof, let it be conſidered, that the Goſpel muſt be preached both to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> tis likely generally, if not to all Nations: <hi>how</hi> elſe <hi>ſhall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear without a Preacher? and how ſhall they preach except they be ſent? ſo then Faith cometh by hearing:</hi> I might aſk how ſhall they underſtand what they hear, except it be ſpoken in their own Language? Tis poſſible, they may receive Conviction of Unbelief, by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153637:42"/>Viſion, by looking on him whom they have peirced, and other <hi>Gentile</hi> Nations together with them: for <hi>when he comes with Clouds, every Eye ſhall ſee him, Rev.</hi> 1.7: but yet there is ſomething more neceſſary to Salvation beſides Conviction of Sin. The <hi>Jews</hi> were convinced and <hi>Pricked at the Heart, Act.</hi> 2.37; but yet they did not know what to do, till <hi>Peter</hi> old them, that <hi>they muſt repent and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized</hi> before they could <hi>receive the Gift of the holy Ghoſt. Paul</hi> was convinced both by Voice and Viſion; but yet did not know what to do, nor would CHRIST tell him, but ſends him to <hi>Ananias,</hi> and he was to tell him, what he ſhould do, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6. The <hi>Jaylor</hi> was convinced by an Earthquake; but yet did not know what to do to be ſaved, till told by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CHRIST hath <hi>a great Harveſt</hi> yet to fetch in, all the World over, both among <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and it will not come in without <hi>a great many Hands;</hi> and we pray for the Coming in of it; but never think of <hi>Hands:</hi> but CHRIST will find <hi>Hands</hi> and qualify them for his Service; he did ſo at <hi>his laſt Harveſt;</hi> he poured out his Spirit upon them by <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts, without which they could not Work: and why may we not think he will do it again? The <hi>ſame Promiſe of the Father,</hi> by Vertue of which the Spirit was then given, for any Thing I know, ſtill remains good, and is not out of Date, nor fully accompliſhed till this Work be done alſo. And if we pray the Lord of the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt to ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt, he will do it, tho' we cannot tell <hi>who</hi> or <hi>what</hi> they will be.</p>
            <p>And when <hi>this Harveſt</hi> is over, CHRIST hath <hi>another Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt;</hi> and this is a great Harveſt too: and this muſt be done with <hi>other Inſtruments, Swords</hi> and <hi>Sickles, Chap.</hi> 3.10.13: <hi>Plowſhares muſt be beaten into Swords, and Pruning-hooks into Spears:</hi> when their Wickedneſs is great, then the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt is ripe; and then put in the Sickle. We have a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſcription of <hi>this Harveſt, Rev.</hi> 14.16; where CHRIST is brought in, or repreſented to us, <hi>ſitting on a Cloud with a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153637:43"/>ſharp Sickle in his Hand; and an Angel crying to him, thruſt in thy Sickle, and reap, for the Harveſt of the Earth is ripe; and he that ſat on the Cloud thruſt in his Sickle, and the Earth was reaped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Thing is ſignified to us both by <hi>Joel</hi> and <hi>John</hi> by <hi>a Vintage,</hi> and <hi>the Cry of an Angel to him that had the ſharp Sickle, to thruſt in his Sickle and gather the Cluſtors of the Vine of the Earth, for her Grapes are fully ripe; and the Angel thruſt in his Sickle into the Earth, and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Vine of the Earth, and caſt it into the great Wine-preſs of the Wrath of God; and the Wine-preſs was trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den without the City; and Blood came out of the Wine-preſs, even unto the Horſe Bridles, by the Space of a Thouſand and ſix Hundred Furlongs.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> I underſtand to be <hi>the great and terrible Day of the Lord,</hi> of which the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>this Context;</hi> and <hi>the Battle of the great Day of God Almighty, Rev.</hi> 16.14; mentioned alſo <hi>Zec.</hi> 14.2.3, and elſewhere in Scripture. But of this I have written more fully when we ſpake of the <hi>great Battle</hi> of <hi>Gog and Magog,</hi> to which the Reader is referred: and this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive will be the <hi>pouring out</hi> of <hi>the laſt Vial,</hi> when <hi>the great Voice ſhall be heard out of the Temple of Heaven and from the Throne, ſaying,</hi> IT IS DONE!</p>
            <p>Thus although I have written but a little, yet it is more than I intended when I firſt began, but not half ſo much as might have been written to every one of theſe Things, nor by far what hath been written by others upon theſe Subjects: but I would not impoſe upon any Man's Underſtanding, nor be offended with ſuch as are otherwiſe minded: yet they may do well, without Prejudice, impartially to ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee whether theſe Things be ſo or no?</p>
            <p>And now for a CONCLUSION, I ſhall propoſe <hi>ſome uſeful Conſiderations</hi> touching what hath been mentioned in this Diſcourſe. And, <hi>firſt,</hi> we may take Notice, by this little Scrip, <hi>how much</hi> and <hi>how many great Things God hath yet
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153637:43"/>to do in the World;</hi> how much of the Prophetical Part of the Scripture is yet unfulfilled; how many great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Things are yet unaccompliſhed, which are to be done now in <hi>this laſt Age of the World;</hi> in the Deliverance of his Church &amp; People out of the Hands of all their Adverſaries, Power, and the Deſtruction of all the Enemeies of Chriſt and his Kingdom; in bringing about all his glorious Deſigns, which he hath purpoſed in himſelf, and hath promiſed the Accompliſhment of for his own Glory, and the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom of Chriſt in this Worl; when all the Kingdoms of this World ſhall be his, and he ſhall reign, and his Name be great from the riſing of the Sun to the going down of the ſame: a little, and but a little thereof, hath been hinted in this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I further propoſe, that ſeeing theſe Things, and many Things more which might be named, muſt come to paſs; <hi>what Manner of Perſons ought we to be in all holy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and Godlineſs?</hi> Looking for, and haſtening to, the Coming of the Day of God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; that we may be found of him in Peace, without Spot and Blameleſs at his Appearing, and be like good Servants, having our Loins girt and our Lights burning; waiting for the Coming of their Lord; and looking for that bleſſed Hope, and the glorious Appearnce of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: and bleſſed is that Servant whom, when his Lord cometh, he ſhall find ſo doing!</p>
            <p>I likewiſe propoſe to Conſideration, that it is a <hi>great Duty</hi> incumbent on <hi>all Chriſtians</hi> at <hi>all Times,</hi> not only to <hi>wait,</hi> but to <hi>watch.</hi> Hardly any Duty more preſt in Scripture than this; Chriſt foreſeeing that wiſe Virgins as well as fooliſh would be apt to <hi>ſlumber</hi> and <hi>ſleep,</hi> when he ſhould come. This watching is that which is in direct Oppoſition to <hi>carnal Security:</hi> we ſhall give a few Inſtances. The Apoſtle 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.6, ſpeaking of the Day of the Lord Coming as a Thief, he warns them to <hi>watch and be ſober. Luk.</hi> 21.36, Chriſt, upon the ſame Conſideration, gives the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153637:44"/>like Council, <hi>watch &amp; pray,</hi> that ye may be counted worthy to ſtand before the Son of Man: And <hi>Mark</hi> 13.33, Chriſt gives Caution, to <hi>take Heed watch and pray;</hi> for ye know not when the Time is; and <hi>ver.</hi> 35, <hi>watch ye therefore;</hi> for ye know not when the Maſter of the Houſe cometh: Again, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.42, <hi>watch therefore;</hi> for ye know not what Hour your Lord doth come: all which implieth, that Chriſt would come in ſuch a Time, when the World would be <hi>aſleep:</hi> at <hi>Midnight</hi> was the Cry made, behold the Bridegroom cometh; in a Time wherein he is not looked for; and in a Time of <hi>general Security,</hi> when Men ſhall ſay Peace and Safety, and as a Snare that Day will come on all them that dwell on the Earth. God hath made <hi>every Man</hi> a <hi>Watchman; Mark</hi> 13.37, <hi>That which I ſay unto you I ſay unto all,</hi> WATCH: but ſome are <hi>ſo</hi> in a <hi>ſpecial Manner,</hi> by <hi>Office;</hi> and tis very dangerous for <hi>thoſe</hi> to ſleep, and cauſe others ſo to do by their Example: the evil Servant did not ſay in his Heat, that his Lord would never come; but he thought (as many good Servants now do) that it would be a great While firſt; not till the general Judgment, and then he knew he would come. Oh let none of Chriſt's good Servants ſay, as he did, my Lord delays his Coming, and ſmite your fellow Servants who are in Expectation of him. You ſhould be always ready; or your Lord will come in an Hour ye think not of. And this Coming is <hi>not</hi> meant <hi>only</hi> by Death, or, in any other Way of common Providence; for ſo he is always Coming, and ever hath been; tho' this may be alſo intended: but there is a Coming of his in an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Way; I mean a <hi>perſonal Coming,</hi> when he will not come alone, but bring all his Saints with him: and he hath told us ſo, <hi>Zec.</hi> 4.5; and told us alſo, <hi>why</hi> he will come, and <hi>what he will do</hi> at his Coming; that tis for the Perdition of ungodly Men, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7; and to execute Judgment on them all, <hi>Jude</hi> 15; and to ſet up his Kingdom which he is gone to receive, and to return. Theſe are <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>great Buſineſſes</hi> about which he comes: and this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153637:44"/>being over, I do not know but that he may withdraw his bodily Preſence, and leave the Government of his Kingdom to <hi>his Saints:</hi> for I ſee no Scripture Grounds for his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Preſence any longer. Sure I am, that when he comes to the general Judgment, he will come from Heaven: and this is that Kingdom the <hi>Jews</hi> are in Expectation of, and which is ſo little, too little taken Notice of by <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, what doth this concern us? we are never like to live to ſee this Coming of Chriſt. To them I ſay, as Chriſt did long ago, <hi>of that Day and Hour knoweth no Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now what Matter of <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Rejoicing</hi> is <hi>this</hi> to <hi>all thoſe that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in Sincerity.</hi> Tho' they have never ſeen him with their bodily Eyes; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, rejoice with Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory: who now ſee him but darkly in the Glaſs of the Goſpel, what Joy and Rejoicing may we think there will be when we ſhall ſee him Face to Face? when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him and ſee him as he is, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2; ſee him in all his glorious Excellencies and Perfections; ſee him Coming in the Clouds of Heaven with Power and great Glory the ſecond Time, without Sin to our Salvation; ſee him that hath loved us and ſhed his Blood for us, borne the Curſe and Wrath of God for us, and is now appearing as an Advocate with the Father for us! Oh what a Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raviſhing Sight will this be to every ſincere Soul! <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw but a little in Compariſon of <hi>this,</hi> and that afar of, and he rejoiced and was glad, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.56. And how did <hi>Job</hi> comfort himſelf in this, in the midſt of all his Miſery, that he knew his REDEEMER lived, and that he ſhould ſtand in the latter Day upon the Earth, and that in his Fleſh he ſhould ſee GOD, and that his Eyes ſhould behold him and not another, <hi>Job</hi> 19.25.26! How were the <hi>Diſciples</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with but a Glimpſe of his Glory which they were Eye Witneſſes of, when they were with him in the Holy Mount, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1; <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.4! And good old <hi>Simeon</hi> was ſo
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153637:45"/>tranſported with the Sight of him in the Days of his Fleſh, and when a Child, that he deſired to live no longer! And tis but a little While, before he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry! Oh then all ye his Saints lift up your Heads, for your Redemption draweth nigh and comfort yourſelves with theſe Words.</p>
            <p>And now to <hi>conclude;</hi> what remains but that <hi>we pray</hi> with greateſt Inſtancy and Importunity, and that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, for the Accompliſhment of all theſe Things; pray that CHRIST'S <hi>Kingdom</hi> may come, that his Will may be done in Earth as it is in Heaven; pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> keep not Silence Day nor Night, give the Lord no Reſt; till he make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a Praiſe in the Earth; pray for the Coming of the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> down from Heaven; pray for the Deſtruction of the Kingdom of Darkneſs; pray for the bringing in both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Goſpel, that there may be one Sheep-fold under one Shepherd JESUS CHRIST: to this End pray that the Spirit may be poured out from on High; pray that the Times of refreſhing may come from the Preſence of the Lord, when God will ſend JESUS; pray for the Times of the Reſtitution of all Things, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21; pray for the Accompliſhment of all <hi>Promiſes,</hi> and for fulfilling of all <hi>Propheſies;</hi> pray for the <hi>Coming</hi> of CHRIST: let the Spirit and Bride ſay <hi>come!</hi> Let him that <hi>heareth</hi> ſay <hi>come!</hi> I add, Let him that <hi>readeth</hi> this, ſay come! Rev. 22.17: and the <hi>Anſwer</hi> will be, <hi>Behold I come quickly,</hi> ver. 7; and <hi>behold I come quickly,</hi> ver. 12; <hi>and my Reward is with me, ſurely I come quickly,</hi> ver. 20; quickly, quickly, quickly! AMEN! <hi>veni Domine,</hi> JESU, <hi>veni. Cito!</hi>
            </p>
            <closer rend="italic">
               <dateline> So Prays thy poor unworthy Creature,<lb/> The Author of this Diſcourſe;<lb/> Written with his own Hand,<lb/>
                  <date>In the <hi>Seventy Ninth Year</hi> of his <hi>Age,</hi>
                     <lb/> And in the <hi>Year of our LORD, 1687.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153637:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
